<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lords table. Whether it is to be spread like a table in an inne for all comers? That it ought not so be done is here maintained.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E880_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206596</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865716</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96898)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E880[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lords table. Whether it is to be spread like a table in an inne for all comers? That it ought not so be done is here maintained.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Cripps in Popes-head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Ezekias Woodward.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Close and open communion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LORDS TABLE.</p>
            <p>Whether it is to be ſpread like A Table in an Inne for all comers?</p>
            <p>That it ought not ſo be done is here maintained.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Give not that which is holy unto the dogges,</hi> 
               <bibl>Matth: 7. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>And he ſet the Porters at the Gates of the houſe of the Lord, that none which was uncleane in any thing ſhould enter-in,</hi> 
               <bibl>2 Chron. 23. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Suppoſe him to be the greateſt perſon in the world, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>bleſſed Cup</hi> from my hand, ſigning to all, and ſealing to every beleiver the <hi>Blood</hi> of That <hi>God-Man,</hi> I would rather give him my <hi>heart blood,</hi> than I would give that <hi>Cup</hi> unto him, whileſt he declares himſelfe to be <hi>no Diſciple.</hi> 
               <bibl>Chryſoſt: in Math: 26. Hom: 83. <hi>w.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>They, that give The bread and wine to unworthy ones, are as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Sacriledge every whit, as he would be, who could give the Sacred Body of Chriſt to be torne in peices and eaten by dogges, or trampled-on by Swine. <bibl>
                  <hi>Calv: 4. book of Inſtitutions. Chap:</hi> 12. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelfe, not diſcerning the Lords Body.</hi> 
               <bibl>1 Cor. 11. 29.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> in <hi>Popes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head-Alley.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:117965:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117965:2"/>
            <head>THE SECOND TREATISE, Relating to <hi>The Lords Supper,</hi> And ſecond <hi>Query</hi> thereupon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Whether all are to be admitted to the</hi> Lords Table, <hi>upon account onely of their</hi> Infant Baptiſm, <hi>though aliens from the Common-wealth of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe, having no hope, well ſet and ſetling, and without God in the world?</hi> 
                  <bibl>Eph. 2. 12.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The Negative here alſo is under our maintenance.</p>
            <p>Here are foure things premiſed firſt. Then is ſet downe what the contrary minded have to ſay for the holding forth the Affirmative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the next place we Argue the Negative.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His being a matter of ſuch high concernment to be cleare-in, we will premiſe a few things here alſo to cleare our way into it, and firſt;</p>
                  <p>1. That we little thought, any Godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter would have put this to Queſtion, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all perſons, pell, mell, tag rag, as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay, how ignorant, how prophane, how notorious ſoever for their Deboiſerie, are to have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the <hi>Lord's Table</hi> by priviledge of <hi>Infant Baptiſme;</hi> Surely this Queſtion, <hi>de Juro,</hi> would have been exploded, when our times were at worſt; Archbiſhops and Biſhops at their <hi>Zenith</hi> or hight, what ever their <hi>Vicars, Curats</hi> and <hi>Parſons</hi> did, <hi>de facto,</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117965:3"/> ſome of them, as very varlets, as were thoſe, they did admit; But <hi>de jure,</hi> this ſhould not have been ſo as may be collected by him, that is ordinarily verſed in the old Service-Booke: Specialle that place, which relates to the order ſhould be obſerved in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, together with other <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> and <hi>Canon's,</hi> as to that ſacred adminiſtration, printed ſix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie yeares agoe, and reprinted a few yeares by-paſt. Wee will quote two places onely, one out of the <hi>Canons</hi> of our Church; the other out of the Booke of Common Prayer. The 26 <hi>Canon</hi> ſtraitly chargeth every Miniſter, <q>That he ſhall not in any wiſe admit to the Communion any of his flock, which be openly knowne to live in ſin notorious without repentance.</q> And the Common prayer book, in the Rubrick before the Communion, commandeth, <q>That if any be an open and notorious evill-liver, or have don any wrong to his Neighbour in word or deed, ſo that the Congregation by him is offended, the Miniſter ſhall call him and advertiſe him in any wiſe not to preſume to the Lords-Table, till he hath openly declared himſelfe to have truely repented &amp;c.</q> Therefore we doe not doubt, but the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Presbyterall way (whoſe <hi>Plat-formes</hi> for Church-Diſcipline one of us have read) will riſe up in their might againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hs:</hi> and the men of his way and judgement, who not onely admit, but plead for admittance of any body how ſcandalous ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, (it is a wonder, if thoſe they admit, are worſe then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,) for their <hi>two pence,</hi> leave ſo much behind them, and take damnation with them; did <hi>Judas</hi> doe worſe, that betrayed his Lord and Maſter? This may minde ſome body of what he may have read, was ſpoken of an Arian Heretick, <hi>I ſhall account him a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mihi non alius quàm diabolus, quam diu Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> 
                     <hi>Devill as long as he is an Arian;</hi> and perhaps he may apply it to this Gentleman, the leader of that <hi>drove</hi> or <hi>herd</hi> of Miniſters, who are of the ſame perſwaſion with him; For it may be doubted, That he with his followers, have, to their power, don more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe to the Church of Chriſt, than the moſt pernicious Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick now a dayes hath don. What! A Miniſter of Chriſt, ſpeak<note place="margin">Qui non vivit ut ipſe docuit certum id docu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentum eſt non eſſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> and act ſo, ſo contrary to all men, who walk by the <hi>Rule</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them in Gods Word? You know his practiſe, and you ſhall heare by a little, how much he ſpeaks anon againſt our Lord and Maſter, that you may know how well you have ſpoken in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117965:3"/> of him. He may preach Chriſt, but doing things moſt contrary to the minde of Chriſt, he makes full proofe he is no <hi>Chriſtian; Chriſtianity being nothing elſe but as faire and full a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſtianiſmus est ſimilitudo Dei quantum poſſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ie eſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae naturae.</hi> Juſt. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. ad Anti. <hi>Ratio naturalis poteſt altecari ubi deficis lex.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>drought of God upon the Soule, as the Soule is capable off in this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death;</hi> But ſee how juſtly Sin is called <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> it hath darkned, we feare, the very light of nature in him, or naturall reaſon, which, ſay the Lawyers, may ſpeake where the Law is ſilent, ſo naturall reaſon where the word of God is ſilent; but where the word of God ſpeaketh, reaſon muſt be dumb. Sin hath darkned that common light in the man, as may be feared; And now read him in his writings, how Croſſe he ſtandeth, and acteth to the word of Chriſt; His Bleſſed practiſe among His Diſciples, and Commiſſion given them to the worlds end; Therefore</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>2. WE are, Sir, heartily ſory this ſhould grate ſo hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, but we cannot poſſibly help-it, while you hold ſo faſt to your fore-man, &amp; his <hi>tenent,</hi> as to <hi>free admiſſion of all</hi> (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious for their obſtinate and affected ignorance, as ſome muſt be where all have free admiſſion) <hi>unto the Lords Table;</hi> It will fare the worſe for you, becauſe he is ſo bad; yee agree ſo well here, that we want skill to make difference betwixt you &amp; him, therefore ye will pardon us, if, diſcerning no difference betwixt you, we make none, though full loth we are to Couple you together. But ſith you will have it ſo, ſo it muſt be, and poſſible with ſome men, it may be for your honour; but however we cannot helpe you at all, nor, we ſuppoſe, can you helpe your ſelfe, by that <hi>proviſo</hi> you ſpeake of, which the man of your perſwaſion gives you, <hi>excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</hi> If a perſon, man or woman, ſo notoriouſly vile and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched, that he is more like a <hi>Devill,</hi> than a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> then admit him not, but excommunicate him, Caſt him out. We cannot thank the man for his remedie, It is not worth ſo much (if he had been ſerious therein, which we think he was not, being againſt his own principles) for whether ſhall we caſt him? unles into the ſame place M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</hi> deſerves to be himſelfe caſt (and it is his lighteſt puniſhment; for indeed he hath <hi>offended the Lords little ones</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">Math. 18. 6.</note> one of them we thought till we thought of you) into the Sea
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117965:4"/> with a mill-ſtone about his necke, for all the dry Land is a Church, as you ſo well know, and can make full proofe. In the next place</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>3. WE would ſay in Alluſion to excellent <hi>Calvin's</hi> words,<note place="margin">Si dimidio Chriſti convuti effemus.</note> if <hi>we could be content with half a Chriſt, our work would quickly be at an end, and we ſhould agree;</hi> So if we could be content with an <hi>halfe Reformation</hi> (which will content the Godly party, as the halfe of her deare Child the deare mother) ye do <hi>not bid us the halfe;</hi> no, nor the leaſt part or peice of Reformation; for, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no ſeparation from the world at the Lords Table, where or when will ye ſeperate? All one at the Lords Table, and every where one. The world and you cannot be two, while profeſſedly one at the Lords Table. We will take leave to ſet downe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Burroughs</hi> his words, we have read or heard upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. <hi>Whenſoever you receive the Communion with any Company,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reade Maſter</hi> Palmer, <hi>p. 100.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>you doe Confeſſe your ſelfe to be of the ſame body with that Company. I muſt profeſſe that I doe beleeve my ſelfe to be of the ſame Body that this drunkard is off; this Idolater, this covetous perſon is off; this whore-maſter, this ſwearer is off; joyning with them to eate Bread at the Lords Table,</hi> (where theſe uncleane ones muſt needs be where all are admitted to be) <hi>profeſſing nothing againſt them, nor taking any Courſe at all with them, for the excluſion of them, or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of them-out: Allowance of a thing done, is as good, as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for the doeing of it.</hi> Therefore it concernes us very much to looke unto it, That it be an holy Communion we receive the bread and wine-in. In the laſt place</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>4. WE would adde this; That we are as unable to keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence<note place="margin">Inveniar ſanè ſuperbus ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, omnium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum reus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do impij ſilen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ij non arguar dum dominus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atitur.</note> as we are to ſpeake, as the Learned doe, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, the ordinance of our deareſt Lord and Saviour, ſo propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; His owne order, in His owne houſe, whereof He is ſo tender, ſo blaſphemed; and by thoſe, who ſhould be moſt obſervant thereof; His ſtewards there. We profeſſe we wiſh our eyes foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117965:4"/> of teares, and that our hearts could melt like wax, and our<note place="margin">Luth: ep: ad Staupitium.</note> bowells yearne upon theſe ſtewards in Gods houſe, who admitt all to his Table, come who will all are welcome; Surely if they repent not of theſe horrid doings, the Maſter of the houſe and <hi>Lord</hi> of the Table, will riſe-up againſt theſe ſtewards, as once He did in <hi>Mount Perazim,</hi> He <hi>will be wroth with them as in Mount Gibeon;</hi> for by their meanes it is that a brutiſh, ſottiſh people, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them to eate and drinke at the Lords Table, <hi>doe eate and drinke their owne damnation;</hi> encreaſing their guilt there, and hardning themſelves to their utter ruine, and everlaſting deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And is this nothing? Nothing ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> for which ſome other will deale with him aſſuredly, and <hi>bray him in a morter,</hi> that his folly may depart from him, who ſaith in effect, though not <hi>in terminis; It is nothing to eate and drinke damnation to our ſelves,</hi> as all muſt doe who eate and drinke unworthily, upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count onely of <hi>Infant Baptiſm:</hi> For by Comming, or, raſhly, like <hi>naturall bruite beaſts,</hi> ruſhing to the Lords Table, before the <hi>word of life,</hi> hath brought life to their ſoules, they <hi>eate and drinke judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to themſelves,</hi> and have put themſelves into an utter incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city or impoſſibility ever to be wrought upon thereby, we meane as to the ſtrength and power of ordinary meanes, That worke on other men for their Converſion, who have not willfully perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the holy order of the Lord, which He hath preſcribed, nor preſumptuouſly paſſed over the ordinary meanes of Converſion: They have hard hearts, that doe not melt into teares, beholding a poore ſottiſh people, encreaſing their guilt every day, and more and more hardning themſelves to their eternall ruine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for our deare Lords and Chriſts ſake, whoſe <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> we cannot ſee with patience thus proſtituted to <hi>dogges</hi> and <hi>ſwine;</hi> for His <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Truths</hi> ſake, the onely two dearely beloved and regarded in the whole world, for Soules ſake, purchaſed at ſo deare a rate, (which argues the pretiouſneſſe of them) for your owne ſakes, whoſe foot ſtands fixed in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> way (<hi>his owne</hi>) a way <hi>of ſin</hi> and death; have we ſpoken hitherto, and ſhall ſpeake in theſe matters before us, as we have beleived, And as the Church of Chriſt hath practiſed in all times, and ages, though not with that freedome and bleſſed <hi>libertie,</hi> as by the abundant riches of Gods goodneſſe now they can doe, for which <hi>liberty</hi> they bleſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117965:5"/> God night and day, who hath ſo changed the times; Time was, and it was a ſad time, with all the godly Miniſters and people all over the Land, when there was no <hi>barre</hi> to keepe any from the Lords Table, but one, which <hi>ſuperſtition made;</hi> And was it a juſt Greife (to borrow M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Sanders</hi> words) then, that there was no barre; And is it your worke now to remove the Barres, yea the Lords and his Churches antient <hi>Land-markes,</hi> and lay all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? The Lord God of gods lookes upon this, and will require it. Therefore in our tendereſt reſpects unto you, we would Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you in our entrance to this Treatiſe, for with that or the like unto it we meane to end this; <hi>of all murther take heed of Soules</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Eccleſ: lib. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>murther,</hi> your owne or others, It is <hi>Salvians</hi> Caution. It is true your people will be very wroth with you, if you will not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them, let <hi>them eate and drinke damnation to themſelves.</hi> The moſt cruell &amp; bloody murther (though M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> will not beleive it) to ſuffer perſons one or more to <hi>poiſon themſelves with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which workes ſtrongly, and kills preſently, as poiſon mixed with the ſtrongeſt wine will doe. Vineger, you have read, 'tis <hi>filius vini,</hi> and the ſweeteſt wine degenerates into the ſharpeſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Goſpel Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to a fowle heart are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> deadlieſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yſon. Mr.</hi> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d. Sp. Ad. 470.</note> vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; As there are more liberall <hi>doles</hi> of Grace in time of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and ſpecially given forth at the <hi>Lords Table</hi> to the worthy receivers; So are there the largeſt <hi>violls</hi> of wrath there alſo, given forth to eate and drinke downe by the unworthy receivers: very likely your people will not apply their heart to this, no not to this; But if they may not have the Lords Supper, as formerly they have had, once a yeare at leaſt (which now will not ſerve their turne) or thrice, or, ſince they are uſed to it, once a moneth; they will crie-out againſt you all the yeare long, and Curſe too; (to whom God hath not made it manifeſt, that they themſelves are beaſts) Theſe ignorant, unreaſonable and wicked perſons will ſo doe, if you will not ſuffer them to drinke downe a Curſe, and deſtroy themſelves for ever, if you will not take the readieſt way, to deſtroy them by admitting them ſo unworthy to the Lords Table, They will deſtroy you; at leaſt they will doe, what they can. Why but, as the Counſell is to the Parent Correcting his Child, <hi>Let not thy ſoule ſpare for his crying:</hi> So regard not their Crie, nor their Curſe neither. But, though they Curſe, Bleſſe them, which you cannot doe; but in bidding them attend dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117965:5"/> upon the <hi>Converting ordinance,</hi> and forbeare comming to the Lords Table, till the Word preached hath done its worke, Then come and wellcome.—But we ſhall contribute more to this, at the end of this Treatiſe. And now before we come to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the Negative; That <hi>Children in underſtanding willfully ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Children of Belial alwayes, are not to be admitted to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> We will with your leave heare you make out the Affimative firſt, <hi>That Children in underſtanding are to be admitted to the Lords Table.</hi> We have heard you (we ſhall alledge nothing from what we have read) and thoſe in your way with you, make it out thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo this is your firſt proofe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ely all our forefathers were not all miſtaken, but they gave it forth to all, all along, till within theſe very few yeares, which they had not done, if they had not thought it lawfull to be done.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is hard to prove this, nay we thinke it is impoſſible; Though we grant that many the excellent of the earth, did give forth theſe<note place="margin">It is hard e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for good men not to be c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ied dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e the ſtreame, when at once they goe with the wind of <hi>example</hi> and tide of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Read Mr. <hi>Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Evang. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> pag. 227, 228. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> ſeales to as many as came for them, and that was juſt, as you ſay, to all; And truely much might be ſaid to excuſe theſe excellent of the Earth, <hi>à tanto,</hi> if not <hi>à toto.</hi> The <hi>tyranny of Cuſtome,</hi> as a tide or torrent impetuouſly running all one way, and carrying all with it; The Tyranny of Biſhops alſo, as faſt friends to Chriſt, many of them, as were theſe excellent of the Earth then, and now faſt friends to Anti-chriſt. Indeed <hi>Iſſachars</hi>—we had almoſt ſaid, <hi>curſe</hi> (but to all His God turned it into a bleſſing) was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the good Miniſters, and people, they lay <hi>couching under bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens;</hi> and this <hi>diſpirits</hi> both Miniſters and people, ſo that with him in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> if we may alude to it, <hi>gemens, ſequitur tamen,</hi> they ſighed, and they groaned, yet they <hi>followed the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And ſurely we may adde this, how did they breath after Reformation in theſe matters? And when they ſaw no amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we know whether ſome of them went, for it is knowne in all the Earth; and how did they there, And the faithfull here <hi>wreſtle</hi> with their God about theſe things? And what thankes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117965:6"/> can they Render to God for what He hath done in way of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to their prayers? Time was when another Girded theſe faithfull men, and carried them whether they would not; but now, bleſſed be God, they have a bleſſed liberty, to Gird them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the <hi>All-might</hi> of their God, according to <hi>His Glorious power,</hi> to <hi>walke whether they would in all pleaſing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This we deſire to leave upon your ſerious thoughts, what uſe and improvement is made of this liberty? or whether not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as an <hi>occaſion to the fleſh,</hi> by men of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> perſwaſion?</p>
                  <p>And yet Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt make bold to tell you, your proofe is naught, and proves nothing, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                              <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> haereſis eſt etiam v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>us conſuciu<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>o.</hi> Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt is <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>y Antiquity, That He did, and that He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pake, ſaid <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ius</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll not me it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtoma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ily ſo done, but tell me what ought to be done. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. ſo an old Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved his friend <hi>A. Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. lib. 10. c. 19.</hi>
                     </note> What have we to doe with th' ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and wants of our Fathers? they are no rules of our faith, or for our walking; It is not what was done, but what ought to be done If ſuch a proofe may be warranted, what evill may not be approved good and be juſtified? Here the Heretique <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſic à progenitoribus accipiens credidi</hi> &amp;c. <q>"This faith have I received from my Anceſtours, in this faith I was borne, and Baptiſed, and in the ſame I deſire to dye:</q> and yet the ſame faith was an errour, and no faith. Full-up to the ſame words ſaid another as very an Heretique as the former; <hi>Quemadmodum ab inſantiâ edoctus ſum, it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Credidi &amp; Credo;</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>As I have been taught from my Childhood, ſo I have beleived, and ſo I beleive ſtill.</hi>
                     </q> And the Idolatrous <hi>Jewes</hi> ſay much the ſame; <hi>So we have done, and our Fathers before us, our Kings and our Princes, and ſo we will doe.</hi> But Sir, we ſpeake to you in our <hi>Jewells</hi> words; <q>We ſit not in Judgement to Condemne our Fathers, God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is their Judge, and He knoweth how to deliver His owne; He was able to preſerve the Buſh in the midſt of the flame; and <hi>Daniell</hi> in the Cave, in the mids of the Lyons; And the three Chrildren in the midſt of the furnace of flaming fire; and His people <hi>Iſraell</hi> in the midſt of the red Sea: even ſo was He able to preſerve His owne in the midſt of that deadly time of darkneſſe. <hi>Ignoſci potuit ſimpliciter erranti, poſt inſpiratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veri</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that erreth of ſimplicity (as our Fathers did) may be pardoned;</hi> The times of that ignorance God might <hi>winke</hi> at. But after that once God hath inſpired the heart, and revealed His truth, whoſoever continueth in his errour, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth without pardon of ignorance, for he is over-borne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117965:6"/> with preſumption and willfullneſſe:</q> Theſe, we have heard, are the words of <hi>Cyprian;</hi> and this ſhall ſerve for Anſwer to what our Fathers did: their doeings are no preſcriptions for us. The word of our God is the Rule of our practiſe in all things; And we humbly conceive, it lyeth open before us as to this particular, as our <hi>Cynoſure</hi> or Starre to direct us; whereof anon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>WE have heard it ſaid, to beare you out in your doings; That lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed and Godly men, doe as you doe, at this day in point of admiſſion to the Lords Table.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>We oppoſe not here, nor gaine-ſay what is ſaid of their Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Godlineſſe. But this we ſay, That your proofe is naught ſtill, and proves nothing. There were learned and Godly men ſure among thoſe thouſands of <hi>Iſraell</hi> called together by King <hi>David</hi> for the removing of the Arke, and yet they put it in a<note place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1 Chron. 13. Exod. 25. 14. Numb. 4. 15. &amp; 7. 19.</note> Cart, againſt the expreſſe Command of their God, which was <hi>that the Levites ſhould beare it on their ſhoulders.</hi> Godlineſſe, we ſee, doth not priviledge us from erring, no not in the Higheſt matters, the Concernments of the Lord and His Chriſt. And for <hi>learning,</hi> the Lord proſper it, and ſanctifie it, that it may be of uſe to His Sanctuary; for this we finde by dayly experience (we will borrow the words of that excellent Expoſitor upon <hi>Job</hi>)<note place="margin">Chap. 4 12.</note> 
                     <hi>It is Satans worke to ſollicite the Learning of men</hi> (even as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer ſollicites the beauty of women) <hi>that he may commit folly with it, and beget ſome monſtrous birth of miſchiefe and villany.</hi> We proceed to that you ſay in the third place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>THat Charity commands you to account all that are borne and Baptized in <hi>England,</hi> Beleivers, Diſciples, and Saints, and upon that ſcore, as their Children are to be admitted to Baptiſme, ſo the Parents to the Lords Table.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As Charitable</hi> as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> is, who hopes the Beſt of all, ſo he ſaith; and, ſay we if of all, then he hopes the Beſt of the worſt of all; what hope hath he of the Devill? Why, If he be a <hi>Devill
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117965:7"/> incarnate,</hi> and baptized, he ſhall be admitted to the Lords Table, though truely we know not well what to ſay more, having hinted ſo much to it before; yet this we will add, That <hi>Charity</hi> doth<note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad Mr. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. pag. 70, 71</hi>
                     </note> both heare and ſee, and hath a rule, whereby to judge righteous Judgement, as of a tree by the fruits; of M <hi>H:</hi> his walke in the ſtreete, by his practiſe at the Lords Table; for if naught there, it is our feare, he is good no where; Thus we judge of a man by<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 16. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> his workes. And to the thing in hand, of a <hi>beleiver</hi> by his faith; of a <hi>Diſciple,</hi> by his diſcipline; his ſchollar-like ſubmitting himſelfe to the teaching of Chriſt; of a <hi>Saint</hi> by his holineſſe. But when none of all this is viſible, but the Contrary to all this, They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themſelves Saints, are dealt with as Saints, yet they revile the Saints, hate and perſecute holineſſe: then we ſee not why Charity ſhould make her mantle ſo large, as thereby to Cover that, which is ſo apparent, that it cannot be hid. When the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance in the heart, the Treaſure there venteth or broacheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſelfe, by the eye, tongue, or hand, then it is eaſie to judge, <hi>Salvâ Charitate,</hi> That the Treaſure <hi>within is evill,</hi> for it <hi>bringeth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.</note> 
                     <hi>forth evill things.</hi> The Phyſitian judgeth of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſicke mans ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke by his tongue, that is foule, the ſtomack is much fowler, being the Cauſe of the tongues fouleneſſe; When we obſerve the ſmoake breaking-out of the doores and windowes, and from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tyles, we conclude, there is much ſmoake within and ſome fire alſo, which, if Care be not taken, will breake-out anon. I ſee thy heart, ſaid one through thy hand, which acteth thy heart, bringing it forth to light. We judge the tree by the fruit, which is not raſh, becauſe it is not ours, but the judgement of the word of God. We have heard it often ſaid to Godly Miniſters and people; <hi>Ye muſt not judge.</hi> They might as well ſay, you muſt not heare or ſee. We may judge and judge the heart too. What an hell above ground that is, where we ſee what an helliſh life there is. We may judge the thoughts of a man not yet turned from ſinne to God, that thoſe <hi>are onely evill continually</hi> (for ſo<note place="margin">Gen. 6. 5.</note> we are taught to know our ſelves, that we may loath our ſelves). But now, when theſe evill thoughts have <hi>minted</hi> or moulded-out themſelves, by words and deeds, then thoughts become viſible. We know the <hi>Mint</hi> in the heart, and what ſtampe it beareth, for we finde it upon mens words and deeds, which are, as we may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117965:7"/> ſay, the <hi>money</hi> that is coyned there: It is probable this laſt ſaid remembers you of <hi>Salvian's</hi> words; <hi>I can tell you anon</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lt quiſpiam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e quid in templo homin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gitave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> quid ſe qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 3. p.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> to his hearers) <hi>what your thoughts are now, you are hearing; when I obſerve you, ſo ſoone as you are out of Gods houſe, running e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man after his profits and pleaſures; I kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w full well your thoughts were upon them, while you were within: What the heart thinketh,</hi> the <hi>hand and tongue minteth,</hi> was the Proverb with him; and much the ſame with ours; <hi>Words and workes make a cleare Commentary upon the heart:</hi> theſe are the hearts Heraulds, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the fooles fooliſhneſs. Yet indeed ſome of your <hi>beleivers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note> 
                     <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> are ſo evill, that wee need not (but that we muſt) obſerve either their words or workes, for <hi>the ſhew of their</hi>
                     <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a 3.</note> 
                     <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ntenance doth witneſſe againſt them, and they declare their ſinne. as Sodome, they hide it not.</hi> To put a cloſe to this; <hi>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccultis ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat Deus, God judgeth of things which appeare not,</hi> The face of the heart being as viſible to Him, as is the face to us, and the darkeſt roome lightſome; But we may judge of things that doe appeare: <q>As the Church judgeth not of hidden Crimes, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the faithfull, judge of the Churches by their hidden Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, but by their open ſcandalls in doctrine and life,</q> ſaid that excellently learned man Mr <hi>Cotton.</hi> When ye ſee men wallowing in the <hi>pollutions</hi> of the world like ſwine in the mire, ye have war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant enough to call them ſwine, and account them <hi>loathſome</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to excommunicate them the Lords Table, as yee will ſwine from yours. Wee charge too deeply, if ſo deepe as the heart, before the heart hath opened its owne ſinke, and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red its owne filthineſſe; but when it proclaimes its fooliſhneſſe, as we read, then may we heare it and beleive it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>4. YOu ſay you know not why there ſhould not be now as free admiſſion to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> as in thoſe primitive times, there was to <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this we might onely, ſay as before, when you mention to us that <hi>Nationall Church,</hi> we ſhould mention to you that <hi>Nationall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>diſcipline.</hi> As thus; If ſo be the hire of a whore muſt not be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117965:8"/> brought into the houſe of the Lord, why ſhould the Child borne of a whore, be brought in thither. But indeed there was proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt this, for the whore, if the daughter of a Prieſt, was to be <hi>burnt with fire;</hi> if the daughter of a more ordinary man, then<note place="margin">Levit. 20. 9. Deut. 22. 21.</note> ſhe was to be ſtoned with ſtones, And the Adulterer with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſſe were both to dye. So Sir, your Argument holds not, nor Can it beare out, as we thinke, this Cuſtome amongſt you, admitting ſuch Infants now (for they are admitted in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents right) to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> begotten, as is notoriouſly knowne, in<note place="margin">Vid: Ameſ: de Conſt. cap. 27. l. 7.</note> adultery, and the Parents not ſo much as profeſſing repentance for the ſin; And ſo giving ſome ſatisfaction to the Congregation thereby. Sir, The Lord will require this at theſe Parents hands (for ſo we may call them) ſo alſo at his hands who ſo preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly baptizeth their Infants. Nor ſhall it helpe him or them; That though the Child was begot in Adulterie, yet it was borne in wedlocke; So have they plaiſtered over that horrible ſin, for which the Miniſter muſt be as reſponſible, we meane for marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, as he ſhall be for Baptizing their Infant, before an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement was made openly before the Congregation, for ſo openly had they ſinned. But the Lord lookes upon this and tells us with a voyce as loud as thunder, that ſith man doth not, He Himſelfe <hi>will be the avenger of theſe things.</hi> And <hi>if the people</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Levit. 20. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>of the Land</hi>—&amp;c. for we would leave it upon your thoughts, that if you, or any brother in office with you, have been or are faulty in this matter, <hi>ye may heare and feare, and doe no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly;</hi> In the ſhutting up of this we humbly remind you, of your owne Principles, <hi>every head of a family</hi> (being by our<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nf. Bap. 61.</note> principles) an <hi>Abraham to his family.</hi> But how if he be an <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maell,</hi> worſe than an Infidell to his family, how then in point of admiſſion of his Children to Baptiſme, or himſelfe to the Lords Table? muſt he, having blaſphemed the one Sacrament, be privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged thereby to blaſpheme the other? or having denied and renounced his Baptiſme, as the manner of ſome is, by his workes, making full proofe he hath very ill husbanded that pretious Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, muſt he be priviledged thereby to deale ſo with the other? Yes ſay you, and accordingly you deale-out unto him. But did your Lord Chriſt deale ſo with His Talents? <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 28.—But wee referre it to the ſixt Treatiſe.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117965:8"/>
                  <p>2. Now as to admiſſion to the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> which you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay, was free to all, which pleads for the like free admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lords Table. That ſpoken before might ſerve here, But, to let that paſſe, we verily beleive there was not ſuch free admiſſion to the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> as you would ſeeme to hold-out, or take for granted; And this our beleife wee ground on the Scriptures of God as we ought, and you expect we ſhould, and indeed Commanded us; which needed not, for God commands us ſo to doe; We humbly conceive there is much in this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we reade; <hi>When your Children ſhall ſay unto you, what meane</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 12. 26, 27.</note> 
                     <hi>you by this ſervice? That ye ſhall ſay it is the ſacrifice of the Lords Paſſeover;</hi> Wee Collect from hence; That the perſons were to be <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> perſons in the matters of their God, the great Concernments of their ſoules, and ſo knowing and underſtanding, as that they muſt be able to inſtruct and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſe their Children in thoſe High points. Now if you finde the Parents ſuch knowing and underſtanding perſons; you may finde reaſon and warrant enough to admit them to the Lords Table; But if very ignorant, yea Brutiſhly ignorant, for ſuch they are, whom you have admitted, then ſeeke your warrant elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where for your admiſſion to the Lords Table; for wee are verily perſwaded you will not finde it from the <hi>Paſſeover;</hi> The free ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they had to that, Sir, be well aware what you ſay, and as well aware what you doe; <q>Take heed of admitting (we adviſe you in worthy <hi>Hilderſam's</hi> word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>) ſuch as are knowne to the Congregation, to be <hi>ignorant, malicious, uncleane, unjuſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, drunkards, Blaſphemers;</hi> Make not the houſe of God as <hi>a Common Inne,</hi> that receives Gueſts of all ſorts, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines all alike. The Gates of Gods houſe are called the <hi>Gates</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> None ſhould preſume to enter into them (at leaſt you ſhould ſuffer none) but ſuch as (in profeſſion and endeavour) are righteous men.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to your Alligation from their free admiſſion to the <hi>Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over;</hi> To our ſeeming it was not ſo free as yours is to the Lords Table For firſt, ſome were to be <hi>Cut-off,</hi> as we read, <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Numb:</hi> 15. 30, 31.</bibl> The ſoule that doth ought preſumptuouſly, whether he be borne in the Land, or a ſtranger, the ſame reproacheth the Lord, and that ſoule ſhall be Cut-off from among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117965:9"/> becauſe he hath deſpiſed the word of the Lord, and hath broken His Commandement, that ſoule ſhall be Cut-off, his <hi>iniquity ſhall be upon him;</hi> Add to this, how deep the Lord Chargeth His Prieſts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 7, 8. Yee have not kept the Charge of mine holy things; In that ye have brought into my Sanctuary Children of a Stanger, uncircumciſed in heart, and uncircumciſed in fleſh. Then at the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe: Thus ſaith the Lord God, No Stranger uncircumciſed in heart, nor uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall enter into my Sanctuary; which was a type or figure of the Spirituall Sanctuary, the Church of the living God in Goſpell times;</q> Whence it may be cleared we think, That, if ſome were to be Cut-off for their wickedneſſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be kept off from the Sanctuary, as well for legall, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for morall uncleanneſſes, ſcandalous ſinnes, then alſo were they kept off from the <hi>Paſſeover;</hi> Yet we thinke the example of Good Rulers, as to this m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tter, cleares this further; They had under the Law by Gods appointment, at the time of their ſolemne aſſemblyes, certaine Levites, that were porters, ſet by <hi>the Gates</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.</note> 
                     <hi>of the houſe of the Lord, that none that was unclean in any thing ſhould enter-in.</hi> And it Commands our marke what diligence was enjoyned them in their office; <hi>The porters waited at every Gate,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 5 15.</note> 
                     <hi>and might not depart from their ſervice.</hi> And hath the Lord Chriſt leſſe Care of His ſervice under the Goſpell, than He had under the Law? Judge you: And take this alſo along with you, if pleaſe you, that you may make righteous Judgement; <hi>None that had any legall uncleanneſſe upon them might eate the Paſſeover,</hi> Numb. 9. 6. And may they be admitted to eate at the Lords Table, who have <hi>reall uncleanneſſe</hi> upon them? Give your judgement here alſo, but looke up to God, and into His Scriptures before you judge. And if it pleaſe you, let the Scriptures be, 2 <hi>Chron: 30. 5. 7. They had not done it a long time in ſuch ſort as it was written.</hi> They had not done it as their firſt fathers did it; who had the pure truth Committed to them, and ſo worſhipped the Lord God purely. But they had done it as their immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forefathers, who were corrupt in their worſhip, and ſo in their practiſe, as theſe had done it ſo did they. <hi>Bee you not like your Fathers,</hi> and <hi>like your Brethren, which treſpaſſed againſt the Lord God of their Fathers, who therefore Gave them up to deſolation,</hi> as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117965:9"/> you ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. This was good Counſell, if it had been taken well; But it was very ill taken, for when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſent the poſts from Citie to Citie through the Countrey of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh,</hi> with this Meſſage, <hi>That he would have a reformation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt inſtitution or patterne, and would not have them doe as their immediate forefathers had done;</hi> It is ſaid verſe 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>; <hi>That they laughed the Meſſengers to ſcorne and mocked them:</hi> What! may we not doe as our Fathers have done? muſt we now be wiſer than they? Yes, ſaith he, you muſt be wiſer than they, and you muſt doe better than they, elſe you will ſhew your ſelves arrand fooles, and utterly undoe your ſelves; for <hi>your fathers were ſtiff-necked,</hi> and <hi>did not yeild themſelves to the Lord to ſerve Him, and to doe as He bad them;</hi> But <hi>they would doe as pleaſed them, and was good in their owne eyes,</hi> and <hi>ſo brought all this evill upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> You muſt not doe as they did, for then you muſt ſuffer as they did; whom <hi>God gave up to deſolation as you ſee.</hi> Now read how theſe words wrought with ſome of them; not a few, the Lord by His Spirit ſetting them home, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. There was a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thoſe matters, and things muſt be done according to their firſt inſtitution. We hope it will teach you very much in point of admiſſion to the Lords Table. And yet to ſet home your leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to helpe you in your choice of fit Gueſts for the Lords Table. Take, in the laſt place, an example from <hi>Ezra, Who would have none to joyne with him in the Paſſeover, But ſuch onely as had ſeperated themſelves from the filthineſſe of the Heathen, and joyned themſelves to Gods people, to ſeeke the Lord God of Iſraell, Ezra</hi> 6. 21. So much to your fourth objection. You have yet more to ſay to juſtifie your Doings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>THat you ſee not why you ſhould exclude any from the Lords Table, becauſe how know you whether they may<note place="margin">
                           <hi>God is the onely <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>wg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ver, and we muſt receive the Law from His mouth. He that will pleaſe God, muſt ſhut all his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations out of doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>es, and have nothing to doe with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>m. We never diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God more than when we take up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o ſerve Him o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r own way; and leaving His rule make a rule for our ſelves.</hi> Mr. C: on <hi>Job</hi> 23. p. 405. <hi>Ab extra ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nario ad ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium non valet argumentum.</hi>
                        </note> not be converted there? It is you know M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> conceite, and we know you have ſaid no leſſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this we ſay, That you give us but your word for this, but give us one word from your God, and we will give you one of our eyes; Then ſearch againe for another word to prove that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117965:10"/> this ſealing ordinance is converting, and give it us, and we will give you the other eye, ſo for two Scriptures you ſhall have two eyes, deare though they are to us, yet not ſo deare as the truth, the leaſt <hi>jóta</hi> whereof is of more account with our God, and ſo with His good people, than are the viſible heavens and the earth. Therefore, Sir, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> (we would rather mention his name than yours, ſo much we favour you) ſhall not put out our eyes with his conceits, now that he hath put out his owne by his <hi>ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> He ſhall not abuſe us as he doth the Scripture ſhamefully af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his manner, touching the Centurions Converſion by ſeeing Chriſt onely upon the Croſſe: It was as mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aculous and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as was the Renting of the vaile and rockes, and opening of the Graves. And he is as well able to prove, That when he laſt adminiſtred this ordinance, he raiſed dead bodies out of the Graves, as that he raiſed dead ſoules, by his adminiſtring to them the Bread and the Wine, which yet is the thing he is to prove, That Converſion, which is the raiſing of the ſoule from its grave, is wrought in this way, we meane by giving out this ordinance; It is true, The people will ſpeake Highly of it, That they never found the <hi>Word</hi> (of Gods grace) ſo prevailing with them, as was that, they heard delivered to them at the graves mouth, and at the Lords Table; But he that cannot ſee, that this is a meere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, and deviſe of Satan, and our owne heart, which is blind and cannot ſee a farre-off, and will make us beleive a lye, That God will ſtep out of His way and worke extraordinarily for us, while we neglect and turne our backs upon the ordinary meanes, He hath appointed for the turning the heart unto Him; We ſhall ſpeake more to this in another place; for the preſent we ſay one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus; That this <hi>tenet, That Sacraments doe convert,</hi> ſenteth ſtrongly of Poperie, and is moſt unſavoury, and loathſome to every good mans heart, being aſſured, That</p>
                  <p>That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord preached is the great Appointment of God, to bring Chriſt and the ſoule together, never to be parted againe. Preaching is the Chariot, that Carrieth Chriſt up and downe the world, here is Chriſt for you, <hi>who ſanctifieth Himſelfe for your ſakes,</hi> That He might doe for you, and in you all that was to be done, and to ſuffer all that was to be ſuffered, for the ſatisfying of His Fathers juſtice, and the Compleating of an everlaſting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117965:10"/> Righteouſneſſe, That ye might be Compleate in Him, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanctified through the Truth, and throughly furniſhed <hi>to every good worke:</hi> Then preaching Chriſt Crucified is the Appointment of God for the ſalvation of ſoules; ſo many Scriptures give-in their evidence, that we know not how many: <hi>The dead ſhall heare</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.</note> 
                     <hi>the voyce of the Son of God</hi> (in the preaching of the Goſpel) <hi>and they that heare</hi> (that is, beleive and obey) <hi>ſhall live. Other ſheepe I have</hi> (He meanes us Gentiles) <hi>them alſo I muſt bring</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn 10. 16. Eph. 5. 14. John 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0. 2 Tim: 1. 10. 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 18. 21. 23. &amp; 2. 14.</note> to the Election of Grace) but how wilt thou bring them Lord? Thou art in Heaven and they on Earth, <hi>they ſhall heare my voice.</hi> The preaching which Chriſt bids His Miniſters preach, is no other but <hi>Chriſts voice,</hi> which bids the ſleeper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, and ariſe from the dead. It is that whereby the Spirit workes faith in the ſoule: it is that whereby <hi>life and immortalitie</hi> is brought to light, through the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> All the Angells in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven cannot convert one ſinner, (it is not their office or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God) But the word preached (which the wiſdome of the world counts <hi>fooliſhneſſe</hi>), converteth all that are converted, being that great Appointment of God for that end. It is juſt ſo with us now, <hi>dry bones,</hi> when Converſion is wrought as once it was; <hi>And as I propheſied there was a noiſe, and behold a ſhaking</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 37. 7. 10</note> 
                     <hi>breath came into them, and they lived and ſtood up upon their feete, an exceeding great Army:</hi> As then ſo now, and to the end of the world, <hi>life and immortalitie is brought to light, into our ſoules by the Goſpell;</hi> It is the Chariot of Chriſt, of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt, The ſaving knowledge, faith in Chriſt, and this by the preaching of the Goſpell, Thereby the <hi>Spirit</hi> flowes into the Heart, and all with Him: Faith the mother Grace with all her daughters all at once, and all together; <hi>While Peter yet ſpake, the Holy Ghoſt fell on them all, which heard the Word,</hi> Acts 10. 44. 11. 15. The Caſe is Cleare; The word preached is the Appointment of Chriſt to quicken the dead; The Sacrament of His body and blood is His Appointment together with His Word to maintaine and quicken that life, when to ſence and feeling it is in a ſwound and fainting away.</p>
                  <p>This being a point of high concernment to be cleare in, we crave leave to proceed farther in it in way of Anſwer to that may be gathered from the holy Scriptures, againſt what hath been laſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117965:11"/> ſaid; <hi>That the word of God where it is preached, is the onely meanes in the Spirits hand of Converſion.</hi> And indeed (to mention it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in paſſage here) ſome Godly Miniſters, as is meet for us to judge, doe aſcribe converſion, not to the <hi>act of receiving,</hi> as the man of your perſwaſion doth; (and truely, we thinke not one godly Miniſter in the world is of the ſame mind with you) but to the exhortations and prayers in uſe at that time before and after the Sacrament is adminiſtred. To this we ſhall ſpeake hereafter in its proper place, where we ſhall tell our perſwaſion as to that matter. So we come to that we intend here.</p>
                  <p>1. It is ſaid, <hi>Rahab</hi> the Harlot had faith, and it ſaved her <hi>from periſhing,</hi> yet living out of the Church ſhe could not heare the<note place="margin">Heb. 11. 31.</note> Word.</p>
                  <p>To this it is anſwered by our <hi>Perkins</hi> of ſweet and pretious memory, <hi>That where ordinary meanes faileth, God can work ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily,</hi> by <hi>reports</hi> and <hi>rumours,</hi> Joſuah 2. 9, 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>2. It is ſaid <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion was <hi>without the Word;</hi> True; it was very extraordinary, immediate by the Lords owne Hand, yet He would put an honour upon the word of His grace, which He hath appointed for converſion. He ſent <hi>Ananias</hi> unto him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. though the great work was don; <hi>for behold he prayes.</hi> And in the next Chapter, <hi>Cornelius</hi> now converted, muſt <hi>ſend for Peter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. It is ſaid, 1 <hi>Pet. 3. 1. That the husband without the Word may be won;</hi> True; Without the word, he may be gained to come to the word, to heare it by the entreaties and perſwaſions of the wife frequenting the meeting place, and by her good example, and Chriſtian carriage, <hi>adorning the word,</hi> which ſhe had heard, ſhe might by the bleſſing of God, win upon him to goe along with her to the place of hearing; his body was drawn within the Church-doores <hi>without the word:</hi> but his heart could not be drawn up to God <hi>without the word,</hi> the Spirit of God and of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry accompanying the ſame, which is learned <hi>Bezaes</hi> interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, the ſumme of it. And we conceive that we reade 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 16. fals under the ſame conſtruction.</p>
                  <p>4. Before we can put a cloſe to this, we would put a Queſtion here, and then put it to the holy Scriptures for reſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; The Queſtion is, <q>
                        <hi>Whether an holy Diſcipline in private
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117965:11"/> houſes,</hi> we meane, <hi>a godly education</hi> there, be not ſufficient to turne the hearts of the Children to God, and to worke in them <hi>a true actuall faith?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before we enquire farther for reſolution hereunto, we would ſay this firſt; That this <hi>ruling well his own houſe, having his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in ſubjection, with all gravity,</hi> workes marveilouſly upon them, making ſuch impreſſions upon the out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard man, as that they looke not as if they had been born dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, <hi>Children under wrath as well as others.</hi> Wee will proceed a little here to witneſſe the honour we give to this <hi>Deſpiſed Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in families;</hi> ſurely a family well <hi>Trained,</hi> diſciplined or Catechiſed, is a very beautifull ſight; as is an Army well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all and every one keeping their ranks, and doing their Duty; A rulers walke before the ruled, if <hi>according to the rule,</hi> together with his exhorting, comforting and charging every one of them, as a <hi>Father doth his children,</hi> is very winning, and gaining upon the whole family, to doe as the Ruler in cheife doth; he being truely and indeed religious, his very example is a <hi>command</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. 18 19.</note>, yea a <hi>compulſion</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Gal 2. 14.</note> to the ruled, ſo as his whole family become reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious too; they give good hopes that way, at leaſt they ſeeme<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. 24. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſo; at the worſt they oppoſe not, for then they know they muſt be no longer there; for a Ruler ſits as <hi>in a Throne</hi> within his own houſe, <hi>and ſcattereth away all evill with his eyes</hi>—For the proofe hereof we entreat the Reader to conſult with the Scriptures in the Margent; <q>We will note but one example of a Ruler, whoſe carriage was ſo gratious in his family, that he made not onely his family, but his whole Court to be a Nurcery of Religion; which may minde us what <hi>Philo Jud:</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he made the <hi>Priſon,</hi> where he was, a <hi>little Temple for the Spirit of God to dwell in.</hi> And indeed it muſt be ſo; He that knowes how to rule his own houſe well, is in a good poſture of ſpirit for publike rule.</q> The ſame wiſdome, and juſtice, and holineſſe for kinde, onely more enlarged and extenſive, acts in eyther ſpheare, and will regularly move in the little and the greater houſe. The ſumme is, A good Ruler, who is <hi>norma publica,</hi> is marvelouſly commanding for good, as an evill example is marvelouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling to evill. Whence the complaints of our Godly Miniſters in all ages, which commands our mark and our mourning.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117965:12"/>
                  <p>We will ſet downe here our excellent <hi>Burroughs</hi> his words upon <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 25. <q>Woe to ſuch parents, whoſe children, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they come to themſelves, ſhall wiſh rather they had been of the generation of Dragons, and off-ſpring of Vipers, than begotten of ſuch parents. Adde hereunto worthy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Burges</hi> his words; It is a woefull curſe to be borne of wicked parents, from whom the Children learne onely to curſe, ſweare, lie and rob, prophane oppoſers of God and Godlineſſe. We will read M <hi>Baxters</hi> words alſo, I know none on earth, that play the<note place="margin">Reſt. 3. 305.</note> part of the Devill himſelfe more truely than theſe men doe; And if any thing that walks in fleſh may be called a Devill, I think it is a parent that hindereth his childe from ſalvation, being careleſſe of his education;</q> He goes on ſpeaking terrible words to careleſſe and negligent parents, as the moſt are, but our ears are <hi>ſealed,</hi> and our conſciences <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ared,</hi> we will not heare.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much to aſſure us, that a pious education, and holy diſcipline doth much where ever it is, and the want of it doth much miſchiefe; but <hi>holy Doctrine</hi> doth all, thereby the <hi>New Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is wrought in young and old by God; whereas by holy diſcipline, our old nature is but painted and varniſhed over, which comes now to be proved when we have ſet downe Mr <hi>Baxters</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pag. 129. 133.</note> words, which ſeeme to us to ſpeak contrary, we will note but one paſſage amongſt many in his booke of <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Aſſembly, I told you before, that gave in their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences about the time and manner of Gods working grace in their hearts did moſt give-in that it began as they thought in youth or childhood, &amp; in very few by the Miniſteriall teaching. And for my own part, I think that if ever I had true actuall faith, it was by the benefit of education before ever I heard a Sermon.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>We would ſpeak three words to this (1) by way of Caution. (2) By way of ſuppoſition (3) poſitively or Concludingly, as we have been taught by our learned Godly Miniſters.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By way of caution, we would wiſh no man to truſt that Converſion, whereof he can give no other Certificate, but that he was virticiouſly educated.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Suppoſe that a parent by his holy Diſcipline and pious edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation had converted his childe by the good hand of God with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117965:12"/> him; we would aske, hath he done this <hi>without the Word?</hi> It could not then be called <hi>holy Diſcipline,</hi> or pious education.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But to ſpeake poſitively, and ſo to conclude this point, <hi>that the word of the Lord may have in all things the pre-eminence; Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or the bringing up of a childe in the Nurture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> is but the externall moulding of a man, not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Renovation of his heart: Education faſhions and frames the outſide onely; Converſion, if true, the inſide; Education chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the actions onely; Converſion not the actions onely, but the Nature alſo; for the effecting whereof there muſt be put forth an <hi>exceeding greatneſſe of Power together with the Word;</hi> once more, and to doe our Utmoſt to drive it home, we are borne every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers child, like <hi>a wild Aſſes Colt,</hi> we love to be free or rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute; we cannot endure to be ſubdued to order, we would know no Law but our own luſts; nor rule but our own deſire; nor be ſervant to any but our own will: Yet the Law of a virtuous edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation paſſing upon us we may be brought into ſome good order and under ſubjection; we may be <hi>canded</hi> over and ſeeme more than Civill: And yet there is as vaſt a difference betwixt what <hi>Education</hi> doth, and the <hi>word preached</hi> doth, as there is betwixt <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> and that is greater than between a mans Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and a beaſt. Education may polliſh and beautifie, yea and rectifie Nature, put it into a pretty frame for a time; But the word preached is appointed for this very thing, to change Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to put it into a right frame, and to ſet it right for ever; To change a ſinner into a Saint; To make a Beleever of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell. Therefore holy <hi>Cowper</hi> taking this very thing into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, <hi>That the word preached is the onely meanes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> would alwayes as he went to Church ſend up this eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation or ſhort prayer, <hi>Lord bow my eare that I may heare thy word,</hi> Amen. He it is, who hath an Almighty Arme, and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it forth by His Spirit with his Word, and ſo maketh it a Converting word, that He in all things may be Glorified through Jeſus Chriſt, To whom be Glory Praiſe and Dominion for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117965:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117965:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117965:14"/>
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>IN the ſixt place we have heard you ſay, that you have done your duty, when you have told your people theirs, and the danger of unworthy receiving, according to the tenour of thoſe dreadfull words they find written, <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27, 28, 29, &amp;c.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>THIS is well, but not the whole of your duty, no; nor the leaſt part. They will not beleive that there is any danger in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, at leaſt, ſuch you ſpeake of unto them, being in your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and upon the ſame ſcore admitted to the Table, <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples and Saints;</hi> why ſhould they Queſtion that, which you doe not queſtion? Let Turkes and Pagans queſtion thoſe matters, and not Diſciples and Saints, we meane Baptized-ones, for <hi>eo nomine</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is good to be ſerious in theſe matters; as to be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in a cold matter is no ſigne of Wiſdome; So to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld in an hot and fervent Buiſineſſe be vrayes folly W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o put three queſtions to you; Th' one relating to a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d on Earth, ſuppoſing, you to be a ſteward in his houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve you to make anſwer to this Lord. The other rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing to the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd of Heaven and Earth,</hi> whoſe ſervant you prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be, and a ſteward in His houſe. The third ſhall be put to your owne ſoule, and as to the other ſo to this make you your anſwer, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God to record upon your ſoule. The firſt</p>
                  <p>1. Suppoſing you to be a ſteward to a great Lord on Earth; would he take it well at your hands? That you counſelled yea threatened a rude and raſcall Company, naſty wretches, and not worthy to enter your Lords houſe, much leſſe to approach His Table, notwithſtanding in they would Come, which yet they Could not without your Connivance, and more, and ſit downe with Him at his Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hips Table. Anſwer this matter to your Great Lord, and ſo we leave it.</p>
                  <p>2. You are a ſervant to your <hi>great Maſter in Heaven,</hi> and you ſay, He hath made you a ſteward in His houſe. Make your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Him, Queſtioning you at this great point; why have you been ſo careleſſe what manner of perſons you have admitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117965:14"/> to my: Table? make Anſwer to Him, we leave this upon your thoughts alſo.</p>
                  <p>3. Put it to your owne Soule, Is it enough to warne Men? we cannot doubt but you have been warning proud men and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous and hypocriticall mockers, and you know whome, and yet they have Come. Doubtleſſe, Sir, you ſhould have reſtrained them from drinking a Cup of poiſon, and from Ruſhing upon their owne damnation. Anſwer this to your owne Soule, and when you are about it, Call God to record therein. Then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you may tremble at <hi>Elies</hi> doome; <hi>I will judge thy houſe for ever, for the iniquity thou knoweſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>thy Sonnes made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vile, and thou Reſtrainedſt them not,</hi> thou didſt not <hi>bend thy brow, nor frowne upon them.</hi> A good <hi>man ſcatters the wicked with his eye,</hi> they ſhall not pertake of holy things, of bread ordained for Children. This ſhall ſuffice for that.—If a Lord on Earth will not take theſe doings at your hand, will your Maſter in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? And if your Conſcience, which is as we may ſay the <hi>Center</hi> of the ſoule, placed betwixt the underſtanding and the will, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Reſult from both: If this your Conſcience acquit you not, God is Greater than your Conſcience, how will you Anſwer Him? It commandeth your ſerious thoughts in debateing theſe matters, and then to give in your Anſwer thereunto.</p>
                  <p>We would remind you of this laſt ſaid, thereby to Render you the more ſerious, That as a ſteward is not to doe any thing, but according to the minde and will of his <hi>Lord:</hi> ſo nor are you in Gods Houſe, but according to the mind and will of Chriſt, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, whome He receiveth; refuſing, whome He refuſeth; Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-out, whome He Caſteth out: whence <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> to receive unto them the weake in faith upon this ground, <hi>Becauſe the Lord hath received him,</hi> Rom: 14. 1, 2, 3. If it be ſaid as a Learned man doth ſay; That the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of a Princes houſe is no rule for the Government of Gods houſe, he is well anſwered, That ſurely 'tis a diſgrace and diſhonour to Gods houſe to be more looſely and diſſolutely ordered, than is the houſe of any Earthly King or Lord. And though the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of Princes houſes, be no rule for the ordering of Gods houſe, yet, methinks, th' ordering of Gods houſe (the King of Kings) might be a rule or patterne (in ſome proportion) for the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of Princes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117965:15"/> houſes; and ſhould not Stewards of Gods houſe bluſh? That theſe ſtewards ſhould be more Carefull about their <hi>Lords houſe,</hi> which is but Earth upon Earth, than Gods ſtewards are of His houſe, which is Heaven upon Earth. <hi>Rejoyce ye Heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>IN the 7th place, you have this to argue for the free admiſſion to the Lords Table: <hi>You Cannot Reſtraine:</hi> It is not in your power to keepe them away: we, ſay you, and they of your way, looke for orders from our Rulers: if they give us power, we ſhall ſee it executed, according as they ſhall preſcribe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So then without a Civill Sanction, we may not expect Church-Reformation. Our excellent <hi>Jewell,</hi> ſpeakes, we thinke, fully and not impertinently to this, as Is generally knowne to all the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Epiſtle concerning the Councill of <hi>Trent;</hi> we will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract<note place="margin">
                        <hi>To ſegni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ur</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in</hi> Venice <hi>p. 859, 860.</hi>
                     </note> a few of his lines, though all are worthy to be heard and read of all men. <q>Then belike, it is not lawfull for any of us to beleive in Chriſt, to profeſſe the Goſpell, to ſerve God aright, to fly Superſtition, and Idolatrie, except they (our Rulers) will give us leave: In humane Counſells it is the part of a wiſe man to expect the Judgement and Conſent of men, But in matters divine Gods word is all in all; The which ſo ſoone as a Godly man hath received, he preſently yeeldeth and ſubmitteth Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; He is not wavering nor expecting others: He underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he is not bound to give eare to (the dictates of men) the Pope or Counſell, but to the will of God, whoſe voyce is to be obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed, though all men ſay nay.</q> If, at the firſt, Chriſt and His Apoſtles had ſtaid for a (Civill Sanction) or Councill, when had their <hi>ſound gone out unto all Lands?</hi>—This is to our ſeeming very applicable to our purpoſe and may anſwer this your plea for a <hi>Civill Sanction</hi> from the Ruler, thereby to impower you, to keep off the <hi>groſſely, obſtinately affectedly ignorant perſons,</hi> thoſe ſons and daughters of <hi>Beliall</hi> (that caſt-off Chriſts yoke) from approaching the Lords Table. If the Rulers would give you power, you would doe it. Poſſibly he may be ſuch an one, that is afraid to hedge-in the Sacrament, and to make it inacceſſible to the ſcandalous and prophane; or to ſettle a faithfull and ſearching
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117965:15"/> Miniſter in the place he lives in, who will, if he will approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe faithfull, make a difference, between the precious and the vile; for then he knowes, he ſhall but make thereby a rod (of Diſcipline) for himſelfe to drive himſelfe forth from that ſacred Aſſembly. Therefore a Godly Miniſter is not to waite the Rulers pleaſure, or a Civill Sanction, as we ſuppoſe.</p>
                  <p>But we crave leave to aske: doe not you derogate much from<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Alas that a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be to be don, but none found to doe it; a power but non to act it; keyes but no hand to hold them, Mr.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nders, <hi>p.</hi> 83.</note> the power your Lord Chriſt hath given you, and entruſted you with? and from the Authority of His word? Is not that ſufficient to beare you out in the ordering matters in Gods houſe as Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards there? <hi>All power is given to Me in heaven and in earth, goe yee therefore</hi> &amp;c. If the Ruler will doe his uttermoſt for your helpe in theſe matters, moveing orderly, and in his ſpheare; And having the Intereſt of Chriſt full in his eye, he ſhall doe well, and his worke ſhall be accepted; But if he forbeare, be it at his perill. You know your duty, Bleſſed are you if you doe it: You ſerve a Good Maſter able to beare you out, if ſo be you order thing; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to His mind and rule of His word. <hi>All</hi> power is His <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally,</hi> and all yours is His <hi>derivatively,</hi> lay out all for Him which you have received from Him, and feare not the face of the Magiſtrate, ſuppoſed ſetting himſelfe againſt you, you have power over him as a Steward in Gods houſe; he none over you in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to theſe ſacred adminiſtrations, as the Churches records, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſacred Scripture tells you. And you may be pleaſed to remember this for your great Comfort; <hi>If through grace,</hi> you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to order matters by the rule of Gods word: <hi>God will not be maſtered by His owne guifts,</hi> nor make <hi>derivative</hi> power, too ſtrong for <hi>originall</hi> power: But bleſſed be God, ye have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe here, the powers on Earth, at preſent, are for you, give en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to you. Yet that there may be no miſtake here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe two great hands, through which the great God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyeth ſo much good to his people, <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> we crave leave to add a little more; The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did aske, as we have heard, what had the Emperour to doe with the Church? To whome it was anſwered, That the Emperour could not rule the Common-wealth, except he governed the Church, for the Church is a Common-wealth. So then, The ordering the matters of Religion belongs to the Care of the Civill Ruler: But then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117965:16"/> we muſt note There are two things in Religion; firſt intrinſecall within the Church, as to preach, Adminiſter the Sacraments, and to ordaine Miniſters, theſe he ought not to doe. But for thoſe things, which are without, thoſe belong unto him; He is to ſee others doe their duty, and Correct them that doe it not: He ought to ſet all ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing, and to reforme abuſes, but not to meddle with things within the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch aforeſaid, as to execute the ſame, but<note place="margin">Read Dr O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon upon Dan: p. 30. &amp; 49, 51, 52, 53.</note> to over-ſee and governe their executions; and thoſe perſons, whoſe proper office it is to execute them. O it is a ſtately ſight to behold that excellent and ſweet harmon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in ſtate, where the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>Miniſter</hi> meet amiably, conſpireing together, who ſhall doe moſt at the ſetting up of the Kingdome of Chriſt, and carrying on His intereſt through the Nation. The truth is, The Lord Chriſt hath been little beholding, to moſt Rulers; that have lived upon Earth, and He hath taken as little care of them, as they tooke little care of His honour. Yet in thoſe ſeirce and perillous times, when the Rulers ſet themſelves againſt the <hi>Lords Chriſt:</hi> There were thoſe and not a few, who in the power of His might ſett themſelves in the Gap for Him, beareing up againſt all the power of the Adverſarie, deſpiſing it and laughing it to ſcorne. And <hi>Luther</hi> was one of theſe in former times (not to mention any more, nor the Worthies of the Lord in our late <q>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times,) In regard of my perſon, ſaid he, I'le fall downe before any: But in regard of the Truths of Chriſt, which I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, I looke on the Kings of th' Earth as <hi>Nitts</hi> or Crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of duſt, (ſo he wrote to our <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th) For a Miniſter that is faithfull in the execution of his office (as ſaid our holy Shepheard) what ever humane weakneſſe there is in him, what ever power there is in others yet he is therein above Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Kings or Angells.</q> But Bleſſed be God, at this day, the powers on Farth are for you, ye may be as holy as ye will, as to the performing the whole ſervice of your Miniſtery: Your Lord hath given you power all-ſufficient; And He inſtruct you to ſound diſcretion how to make a Bleſſed advant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge thereof to His Glory and His Churches good: Amen.</p>
                  <p>Yet we cannot come off from this common plea which is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by all the <hi>herd</hi> that have M <hi>Hs:</hi> for their Leader; <hi>Wee have no power to keepe any how wicked ſoever, from the Lords Table,</hi> ſay
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117965:16"/> they; we would entreat theſe men to call to remembrance, what the Lord ſaith touching the <hi>ſanctifying Himſelfe</hi> upon horri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le ſinners, in caſe the <hi>Rulers</hi> did not We apply it to this in hand,<note place="margin">Levit. 20. 4.</note> If men to whom the Lord hath given Authority to reprove, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and excommunicate wicked men (from communicating at His Table at the leaſt) eyther dare not, or will not doe it; Ile take the matter into My own Hand, Ile doe it ſaith the Lord. And hath not He, with whom is terrible Majeſty, hath He not don it? hath He not executed terrible wrath upon theſe unworthy Receivers at His Table? One fals from an houſe, breaks his bones, perhap; his neck; A ſecond from a tree, or horſe; A third is hurled into the Waters; A fourth is ſuffered to run his <hi>own way,</hi> and ſo to cut-off himſelfe in the midſt of his dayes; A ſift is his own executioner; A ſixt, and he is many, theſe are la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in the lap of their own luſts, and now being paſt feeling give themſelves over to <hi>laſciviouſneſſe, to work all uncleanneſſe with greedineſſe; joyned to their Idols, and let alone;</hi> And hath the Lord dealt leſſe ſeverely with the <hi>Stewards</hi> of His houſe, who have dealt ſo unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ſtewards there? Some He hath thruſt-out. And thoſe that, through favour hold-in for a time, Is not a <hi>viſible ſword up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their arme,</hi> (their power is broken) and upon <hi>their right eye</hi> their underſtanding is darkend. The unfaithfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l Steward, the Idol-Shepheard ſhall be like an Idol, having eyes but ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing not; He was before <hi>a blind S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er</hi> ſinfully; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow he is <hi>a blind Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially. O the dreadfull wayes the Lord takes in the exerciſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication! He that inwardly excommunicates His own dear children, as their ſins may deſerve, and caſts them out of His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence (to uſe the words of that excellent Divine Dr <hi>Goodwin</hi>)<note place="margin">Child of Light p. 137.</note> will He ſpare theſe, who dare out-face him at His own Table (prepared for His own people, <hi>followers of Him as deare Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>) ruſhing-in thether to receive that with their hands, which they blaſpheme with their tongues, and trample under with their feete; and would deale as deſpightfully with His bleſſed perſon now in Glory, as once their forefathers did deale with Him, when He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abernacled in our fleſh, and was on earth amongſt them: will He ſpare theſe or thoſe Miniſters, Stewards in His houſe, that ſuffer a brutiſh ſottiſh people ſo to doe, alledging for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (but will their allegation be accepted) <hi>their Lord put a key
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117965:17"/> into their hands, but they found neyther hand nor heart to uſe it; becauſe the Ruler, forſooth, did not Commiſſion them ſo to doe:</hi> Commiſſion them! A Ruler, as wee ſuppoſe, exceeds the bounds of his Commiſſion, for which he will have no thankes from his God, if he ſhall Commiſſion the Stewards in Gods houſe, how to manage Gods matters there; Wee are taught from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, and from them, that hold thetherto; That in theſe caſes, which relate to Gods houſe, and thoſe ſacred adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there; The Miniſter rather preſcribeth the Magiſtrate, than he the Miniſter; He, the Miniſter of Chriſt, rather gives orders to him, than receives orders from him. Therefore to proceed to a cloſe of this; Will the Lord ſpare theſe Stewards in the day when they muſt give an account of their Stewardſhip, who knew not the extent of their power, and therefore cannot know their duty to doe it; their power and their duty being of equal length? We will conclude in <hi>Davids</hi> words, <hi>My fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and I am afraid of thy judgements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>IN the next place, we have heard that much if not moſt of all the evills of theſe times, is Charged upon the non-admiſſion to the ſealing ordinance; And your ſelfe have not been ſilent this way.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Charge is moſt unworthy a Miniſter of Chriſt; for the contrary thereunto is moſt true; God is diſquieting of us now; He is viſiting upon us the horrid Contempts offered to His word; The horrible prophanations of His day; The abhominations He hath found committed in His houſe, as to thoſe ſacred adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there. And theſe are, as we have juſt cauſe to feare, but the beginning of our ſorrowes, The firſt drops of wrath comming; The Lord God will be prodigall of our blood, becauſe we have been ſo prodigall of His Son's blood, giving it to, or rather caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it away upon thoſe, who cannot but, like ſwine, trample it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-foot. <hi>Prov:</hi> 27. 7. Theſe, you know, are <hi>Calvin's</hi> words. <hi>Son of man, Seeſt thou what abhominations are Committed in My houſe? I have ſworne by the excellency of Jacob</hi> (by Himſelfe) <hi>ſaith the Lord</hi>—for you read it every where. Indeed that <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lua
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117965:17"/> multorum capitum,</hi> we beaſt-like people, we ſay as much with thoſe rebellious and ſtubborne ones, or much after their manner, <hi>Jer:</hi> 44. 17. It was never better with us, then when we had our <hi>Service-booke,</hi> our <hi>Eaſter Communions</hi> &amp;c. But ſhould not you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer us even as <hi>Jeremy</hi> did; <hi>Did not the Lord remember theſe things, and Came they not into His minde? So that the Lord could no longer beare, becauſe of the evill of their doings, and becauſe of the abhominations, which they had Committed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But with your patience, Sir, Give us leave to aske you Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the place where you were borne, and whereunto you wiſh ſo well, and the Good of thoſe ſoules is the Travell of yours; how find you the people there? If they be as bad, as who are worſt, then it is not becauſe they are barred from the <hi>Font,</hi> or the <hi>Lords Table;</hi> for there you know the verieſt varlet in the Towne, (if there be any ſuch which perhaps you queſtion) may have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance with his Children to Baptiſme; and, if he pleaſe may come at the day appointed to the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> as freely as you may come to an Inne, and ſet up your beaſt in the ſtable; And if you were queſtioned about your owne Towne, where you give freedome enough to theſe fore-mentioned places, the <hi>Font,</hi> and the <hi>Table,</hi> for you are of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Hs:</hi> perſwaſion; Wee beleive you could ſpeake little of the good you have wrought among them, by indulging that liberty to bring their Infants to Baptiſme, and anon after themſelves to the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> ignorant though they are ſome of them, whome ye ſo freely admit, as is ignorance it ſelfe. Nay, Sir, to tell you our <hi>faith</hi> in theſe matters, we verily beleive, That Miniſters generally all over the Nation, having mightily obſtructed their Goſpell-worke in the Converſion of Sinners, by ſuffering them to Come to the Table of the Lord, there to receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the bread and wine, before they could give any evidence they had received Him by the <hi>word of hearing;</hi> we meane, by the preaching of the Goſpell: You ſuffer them to ſtep-over the Converting ordinance, and admit them to the ſeale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ordinance, and now you may preach till your lungs are ſpent, and doe no good among them. Indeed this is our <hi>faith,</hi> and which relating to ſuch things, that are the higheſt concernments of Gods Glory, and good of His people, we may not <hi>keepe in to our ſelves.</hi> The great worke and buiſineſſe of preaching is, you know, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117965:18"/> bring Chriſt and the ſoule together; To call them in, who are without; then to confirme and ſtrengthen them being brought in. Now you ſhould, (it is our <hi>faith</hi>) waite Gods time till this be done; till He hath, by His Word and Spirit <hi>gathered</hi> a Church out of a Church (we know this ſounds harſhly in your eares, but why ſhould it ſo) till He hath gathered His Church out of your Church (ſince you make it as wide as the little world in <hi>England</hi>) till He hath taken them out of the world, and added them to His Church, ſet them in a ſafe <note n="*" place="margin">Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſure and immoveable ſtate, fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t upon their Rocke Chriſt, as Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> faſt for evermore. Doe you goe on now to doe your worke, preach the Goſpell, and leave the Reſt to God, patiently waiting His time. But in the meane time, you ſhall never make us beleive, had you the tongue of an Angell, That wicked and unreaſonable men (for they have no faith, which is the reaſon of the ſoule) are the worſe, becauſe they are denied, the Seales of the Covenant; But much worſe (which may be) becauſe they are admitted to pertake of thoſe before their time; for as once it was, ſo it is now, together with <hi>the bread and wine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 13. 2. &amp; 29. 30.</note> the <hi>Devill enters</hi> them too, and now ſee them in their walke, and you ſee Devills incarnate; no difference in their walke, for as they <hi>ſee him doe,</hi> ſo doe they, onely they have fleſh and bones, ſo hath not he.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IX</head>
                  <p>IN the 9th place, and ſo to tell you all that hath been, to our beſt remembrance, told us, thereby to juſtifie your doings in Gods houſe, as to the handing forth thoſe ſacred things there, <q>If the people may not be ſuffered to come to the Lord's Table to receive there, as they expreſſe it, They will not come to the place of hearing to receive the word there, drive <hi>them</hi> from th' one place, and they le drive <hi>you</hi> from th' other; or, if that they cannot doe, they will not come at you; or, if they doe come, they will caſt your <hi>pearles,</hi> whereof you are diſpenſers, the word of God, or Counſells thereof, behind their backes, they will not hearken to you.</q>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this we would reply theſe foure things, and firſt by way of Queſtion.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117965:18"/>
                  <p>1. How would this have ſounded in the Apoſtles eares, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by their Lord to preach unto the Heathen, ſhould theſe Heathen have ſayd to the Apoſtles, <q>
                        <hi>If ye will not Baptize us firſt, we will heare none of your preaching;</hi>
                     </q> We ſay, how would this have been taken by the Apoſtles, ſuppoſed thoſe Heathen had ſpoken unto them theſe words? Verily, for ſo it ſeemes to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Heathen people now adayes, ſpeaking after the rate of thoſe words, before ſuggeſted, ſpeake the very ſame thing; And how u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reaſonable and wicked they ſhew themſelves to be in ſo ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is left upon your thoughts, with this earreſt requeſt, that your thoughts may be ſerious.</p>
                  <p>2 We thinke it will be granted, That the Goſpell is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Treaſure or Talent of price, that can be entruſted with the Children of men, It is that, which liſteth up a people, (whether ye ſpeake of a Nation, or <hi>a man onely,</hi> we allude to that in <hi>Job) as High as heaven.</hi> 
                     <q>It is the <hi>rod of His p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>wer, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r of His</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ob 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Kingdome, the grand Inſtrument</hi> (we will borrow that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently Learned man's words) <hi>whereby He accompliſheth all His</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>deſignes in the world, whether they be for life or for death,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 16. He hath given that a right to take poſſeſſion in His Name, and authority of all that He will owne in any Nation under heaven.</q> Now if this be rejected by us, we will have none of it, unleſſe upon our owne termes, and order of our own ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointment, give us the Body and Blood of Chriſt firſt; As if we would ſay, give us the ſeales of the Covenant, but for the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelfe (opned unto us in the Goſpell) we will have none of that. We were ſaying, <hi>If the Goſpell of the Grace of God be put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 20. 24. Acts 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h. 21. 41.</note> and driven with all our might from us, as that, which is moſt loathed by us, or hatefull to us, we ſhall be <hi>miſerably deſtroyed</hi> anon, as thoſe <hi>Deſpizers,</hi> for we are pointed at there—.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>veſtra res agitur</hi> You know your Lords order, how ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der He is of it, and the judgement that is written ſhall be their portion, <hi>who will remove the bounds, that you may not doe like them.</hi> Yee can take it into your Conſideration, and put it upon ours, That if This Rich Talent, we called the Goſpell, ſo laded with <hi>pearles,</hi> be not uſed and improved firſt; no other <hi>Talent</hi> can; nor can we expect any other <hi>Talent</hi> given to us (in mercy) no more than we can another Goſpell.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:117965:19"/>
                  <p>For the Lord doth not ſay as we fooliſhly may dreame, and doe according as we have dreamed; The man hath not improved his Talent, nay he hath abuſed it: What though, give him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Talent; No, <q>
                        <hi>Take therefore the Talent from him, and give</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Math 25. 28.</note> 
                        <hi>it unto him which hath ten Talents.</hi>
                     </q> The onely wiſe God will not doe as His unwiſe Stewards doe (if He will owne them for His) as to Goſpell Adminiſtrations: The man hath denied re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced his Baptiſme, being <hi>abhominable and to every good worke reprobate;</hi> What though, Admit him to the Lords Table not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. Wee will cloſe with this, and ſo come to the next. Till the Word hath prevailed with us, nothing can, till that hath done us good, nothing ſhall. While the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is trod under-foote in the hearing place, ſo is the ſacred Blood, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at His Table: We cannot reject Him at one place, and receive Him at another; our ſoules are as <hi>full</hi> here as there; and therefore cannot but <hi>loath, trample</hi>-upon Chriſt that <hi>honey-combe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 27. 7.</note> there, as here, as at th' one place of <hi>hearing,</hi> ſo at th' other of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving.</hi> Therefore</p>
                  <p>3. Be not you carefull about this, whether we will <hi>heare or whether we will forbeare;</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>Preach the word, be inſtant, in ſeaſon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e, exhort with all long-ſuffering and doctrine;</hi>
                     </q> This is your Charge from the Lord, And be you aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured you ſhall never make us attend with the eare, giving all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, till you have <hi>bored</hi> the eare; And to <hi>bore the eare</hi> you have no other meanes for it but to preach the word, thereby to make us <hi>obedient</hi> in <hi>word and in deed.</hi> Doe not Entertaine ſuch a thought as this, but ſhew your ſelves men. (1) That we can be brought into Love with the Goſpell, or to receive the Goſpell in love, by giving us admittance to receive at the Lords Table; What can we receive there more than at our owne Table, unleſſe it be a <hi>Curſe,</hi> having not received Chriſt in the Goſpell firſt? (2) That we can be brought over to Chriſt by any other wayes or meanes, but what are of His owne appointing, for His bleſſing accompanies thoſe meanes, as doth His Curſe thoſe preſumers, who thinke to compaſſe their Ends by meanes they have ſhaped, without the leaſt ſhape of reaſon, according to their <hi>owne under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> moſt contrary to Gods word, and an abhorring to His Spirit: Therefore if you have the leaſt hope to prevaile with men,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117965:19"/> prevaile with God firſt by prayer, That you may take the way He Himſelfe, hath by His Word and Spirit paved forth before you; for be you well aſſured, He will not goe out of His owne rode way to meete with you or your people in your by-pathes. In the laſt place,</p>
                  <p>4. And to reply a word from the Lord to thoſe ſtout words mentioned at the beginning, <hi>They will drive away the Word from them,</hi> and the <hi>Preachers of the Word,</hi> if they <hi>will not ſuffer them to receive at the Lords Table.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heare we what the Lord ſaith to theſe, <hi>I will caſt them away as Rubbiſh, filth, and dirt is caſt away:</hi> So He ſaith by His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>My God will caſt them away, becauſe they did not hearken</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſea 9. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>unto Him;</hi> ſuch as will not hearken to the word of God, God<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Read Mr.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yl <hi>upon</hi> Job 8. 20. p. 124. Pſal. 50. 16.</note> will caſt away; why? They caſt God away, when they caſt the word of God away. They caſt the <hi>Covenant</hi> behind their backes, while they hate Inſtruction; No wonder God caſteth them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind His backe (a dreadfull place for our perſons, but a glorious place for our ſins) <hi>For the wickedneſſe of their Doings, I will drive them out of My houſe.</hi> They that drive, ſhall be driven with the Tempeſt of the Lord, as the Thiſtle-downe, dried ſtubble, parched leaves or chaffe before the whirle-wind. God will drive them out of doores, when they drive His Truth out of their hearts, for they would drive it out of His houſe, And the God of Truth out of the world. What they cannot poſſibly doe, they will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour what poſſibly they can to doe. A good Miniſter will drive theſe from the Lords Table too, they ſhall not come neare that, till it can be made to appeare, The word of Gods Grace hath come neare to them, and ſet them in their right mind. So we have Concluded from Scripture premiſes, and ſo proceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. X.</head>
                  <p>10 IN the laſt place, we crave leave to tell you our Jelouſie as to theſe matters, and we entreate you to account it a godly jealouſie, which is this, That there is ſomewhat more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes with you to give ſuch, <hi>free Admiſſion,</hi> as aforeſaid, than all thoſe nine Reaſons, you have given us before, and this is it (to tell you our Jealouſie) when it pleaſed God to reveale His Son
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117965:20"/> in you (ſuch is our hope) that you might <hi>preach Him among the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Heathen</hi> (truely we meane, for we muſt be plaine in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we call a ſpade a ſpade) your <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> (heathen they are as you heard and worſe, till your preaching is come unto them in power) have not you with your Brethren, <hi>conferred</hi> at leaſt with <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> what way you are to take with your people in point of Admiſſion to the Font and Lords Table? You muſt Anſwer this to God, ſith you are Stewards in His houſe, and ſhould know how to behave your ſelves there (with regard enough to that holy guile which is allowed you) for certainly to Him you muſt make Anſwer. We humbly in the feare of our Lord tell you our Jealouſie; For this we know (we are fleſh and blood too) <hi>perſecution</hi> is a very ſore thing to the fleſh, and therefore all its care, deſire, and endeavour is how to Eſcape it; Now there is no way for <hi>a man, that will live godly in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim 3. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt Jeſus to eſcape it,</hi> if he will avoid it, he muſt as to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Ceaſe to be Godly, and ſo he <hi>Conferres</hi> with fleſh and blood; and taking that for the man of his Counſell, <hi>he muſt chooſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ob 26. 21</note> 
                     <hi>iniquity rather than affliction.</hi> It is our Godly Jealouſie, that you and your. Godly Brethren in the ſame way with you, have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred too much with <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> about thoſe ſacred admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, and ſo to avoid perſecution, have done as ye doe, given <hi>free admiſſion</hi> as aforeſaid; If you did not as you doe, you ſhould anger the beſt men in your Pariſh, as they are in account among us now adayes: and ſo you ſhould have their purſes ſhut, and their mouthes wide open againſt you, like Cannons mounted; This is ſore to fleſh and blood, and therefore Conſulting with it; it will direct you another way, to ſave it ſelfe from perſecution; give their Children Baptiſme, and themſelves the Lords Supper; and all ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e well, their purſes ſhall be opened and their mouths ſhutt, unleſſe open to bleſſe and pray for you, dealing ſo kindly with them; but take heed of their bleſſing you, and your bleſſing your ſelfe in ſuch a way with them: and you may remember this with it, That ſome mens Curſing are as good as their bleſſings, and you ſhall proſper better under them; To put a cloſe to this, This is our perſwaſion from what we ſee and heare; ſhould the Goſpell come to us like an Angell, with a ſword in his hand, and with fire in its mouth to kill our luſts and conſume them utterly,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117965:20"/> yet we ſhould never be troubled about it, no nor regard it in the leaſt, If our Miniſter would give us the Lords Supper, before this killing worke were done; what he did in the Pulpit, he would undoe all at the <hi>Table;</hi> If he would preach <hi>hell</hi> to us from th'one place, we would take <hi>heaven</hi> to us at th'other; he ſhall never make us beleive, That we are heathen and worſe; not, that we are all <hi>Children of wrath,</hi> and are every day and houre of the day damneing our ſoules, while we are treaſuring up wrath againſt the day of wrath; he ſhall never make us beleive this, while he puts a Cup of Bleſſing into our hands. And yet if he doth not thus, he ſhall be the <hi>white</hi> and <hi>marke</hi> for wrath &amp; envy to ſhoote all their arrowes againſt you, which fleſh and blood cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; yet doe not <hi>Conferre</hi> with it (it is our Jealouſie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e doe) ye ſhall never pleaſe God then, nor your people for <hi>their good to Edification.</hi> It is the greateſt enemie we have in the world, the Devill and Satan himſelfe not excepted; ye are no <hi>debtours to the fleſh, and owe it nothing but mortification,</hi> as ye tell your people we hope. Well thus we judge of the Holy way, and bleſſed are they that walke in it; fleſh and blood muſt never be Conſulted with about it, it is an adverſary, yea a torment to it, as the holy way is an adverſary to the fleſh, and a Torment to the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Thus we have heard you argueing, the affirmative <hi>for free ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Lords Table,</hi> you will allow us the ſame patience while we argue the Negative, That this free admiſſion to the Lords Table ſo ordinary amongſt us is not according to the mind of God, and preſcript of His word, holding forth our Rule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and thus we Argue it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey are not to be admitted to <hi>feaſt</hi> at the Lords Table, who turne their backes upon the <hi>feaſt of the Goſpell:</hi> we meane thus; They muſt not be ſuffered to Come to<note place="margin">
                        <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>t feaſt to which ſinners are invited, is one<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Word and mind of God in the Goſpell; The word of grace i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the greateſt feaſt which God makes his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Mr</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yl <hi>upon</hi> Job 23. <hi>p. 411.</hi>
                     </note> the Lords Table, there to receive Chriſt Jeſus the Lord in the bread and wine, who reject Him and make light of Him in the tenders and offers of the Goſpell; We ground this upon thoſe knowne Scriptures, whereon we ſhall dwell a little, <hi>Math:</hi> 22. 2.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:117965:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luk:</hi> 14. 16. where we have the Lord of Heaven and Earth, the King of Glory intending to His Church and people the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt preferment, that is imaginable. <hi>He will give His Son, the Heire of the Kingdome to be His Bridegroome.</hi> Now becauſe there is a marveilous diſproportion, as her preſent Caſe is, betwixt this <hi>Bridegroome</hi> and the <hi>Bride,</hi> as vaſt a diſproportion as is betwixt Heaven and Earth, yea we may ſay Heaven and hell: and at as huge a diſtance they ſtand too, This Bridegroome and this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Bride, as heaven and hell doe, and ſuch a gulfe betwixt them. Beſide all this, This intended Bride is a very ill-favoured and froward peice, and as proud as ſhe is uncomely, and as will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alſo as <hi>will</hi> it ſelfe; and, as ſure as death, ſhe will refuſe <hi>life,</hi> ſhe will have none of the match; He ſhall not be her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome; who then? <hi>Any but Hee;</hi> and the truth is (but <hi>nullum tempus occurrit Regi</hi>) The Lord of time may take His own time, and when He pleaſeth) ſhee hath made her own choice and is married already, and wonderouſly ſhee is ſatisfyed in her match: But now here's much to doe, firſt to breake this match, and make it <hi>null,</hi> then to make it an abhorring to her ſoule, that ſhee was ſo haſty, carried-on ſo headlong in the buiſineſſe of ſo high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and then to make her <hi>fitt and prepared</hi> for <hi>her Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome;</hi> then to give her free and full and hearty conſent to Come together, never to be parted more. Now to effect all this God the Father maketh a ſumptuous and glorious feaſt like Himſelfe, the Lord of glory, wherein He holds forth to the world the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant riches of grace and of glory by His Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. And this we doubt not to call <hi>the feaſt of the Goſpell,</hi> whereby this Bridegroome maketh love to His Bride, That ſhall be; and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He is too high and ſtately, yea and too glorious too, to woe in His owne perſon, beſides that His <hi>terrour would make her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 9. 3.</note> He hath His <hi>Para-nymphs</hi> and ſpokes-men for Him, who are His <hi>Maidens,</hi> Miniſters, and Preachers of His Goſpell. And this we take to be the ſcope of this Parable, which you know, <hi>Nihil probat ratione circumferentiae, ſed tantum ratione Centri,</hi> we muſt obſerve whereat it drives, and wherein it <hi>Centers:</hi> And we take in two rules here firſt: for the <hi>ſenſing</hi> of parables and ſimilitudes; and then one thing, which is ſpoken againſt the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing therefrom.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:117965:21"/>
                  <p>1. We obſerve their true ſcope and intendment, and not to<note place="margin">In il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is quae me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>è dicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non oportet accipere ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum omnia.</note> wrench and tenter it beyond that; which, were againſt the Rule, we not <hi>angariari parabolam,</hi> in Compelling it to goe farther then it would.</p>
                  <p>2. What things are ſpoken of God <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, are to be underſtood <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in a ſenſe becomeing God; now in the third place.</p>
                  <p>3. We would take off an objection here before we proceed to our Argument drawne from this Parable, <hi>That there is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueing</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theologia Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolica non eſt argumentativa.</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi> p. 440.</note> 
                     <hi>from Parables, Similitudes</hi> are not <hi>argumentative;</hi> True; <q>ſaith that excellent man, Similitudes argue not, beyond th'ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that particular wherein their nature, as ſuch,</q> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. The intendment of Chriſt in every parable is warily to be obſerved; Therefore, though a Learned man, <hi>Aquinas</hi> himſelfe, as we have heard, hath ſaid as aforeſaid, and better Divines than he; yet by his leave and their favour, we thinke the ſpeech is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Logicall,</hi> nor <hi>Theologicall,</hi> that is, as we are told neither <hi>good Logicke,</hi> nor <hi>good Divinitie:</hi> Not good Logicke, for <hi>Comparata etiam ficta arguunt,</hi> and if they doe argue, then they are argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative and prove ſomething, as ſure as operating is working; Nor <hi>Good Divinity</hi> for if all Scripture be profitable <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 1, 2</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, for <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>reproofe,</hi> then <hi>Symbolica</hi> alſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing by parables: If not, why would Chriſt and ſome Prophets<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> before Him, and <hi>John</hi> th' Apoſtle after Him, delight ſo much in Symboles and parables, if they were not doctrinall, and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative; Theſe things we thought neceſſary to premiſe before we could argue from the Scriptures; firſt to cleare the ſenſe of them, and what their ſcope is, and that we have good warrant to argue from them; and ſecondly, to make it cleare that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> is cleare beſide the ſcope; when he will have the <hi>feaſt</hi> there to be ſolemnized at the Lords Table, belike becauſe <hi>Luke</hi> calleth it a Supper, ſo wiſe a man he is, and ſo rationall a ſchollar in divine matters: for he will have the invitation be as generall, <hi>come ye all to the Lords Table.</hi> But now he will contradict himſelfe, and ſpeake againſt his owne experience. He invites all, and admits all to the Lords Table, and who refuſeth to Come? But there the bulke of the <hi>Jewes</hi> mane <hi>light of the feaſt,</hi> and their invitation to it, and <hi>went their way,</hi> they all with <hi>one Conſent</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luke</hi>)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117965:22"/> made their excuſe, they had matters of more Concernment, as they thought, than that <hi>feaſt</hi> We read alſo how deſpitefully they uſed the ſervant ſent to Call them in; It is certainly the <hi>feaſt of the Goſpell,</hi> that meets with ſuch oppoſition; and as certaine it is That none of <hi>us Gentiles</hi> will Come-in to This <hi>feaſt</hi> neither, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt there, till we ſee need of Him; and that He hath no need of us; for we are in our owne eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, being Convinced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the Word and Spirit, <hi>poore, maimed, halt and blind;</hi> or if<note place="margin">Luke 14. 21. Revel. 3. 17.</note> you pleaſe, <hi>wretched, miſerable and naked;</hi> being Convinced that ſuch we are, In we come then, and not till then, before thus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced. Thus we ſtand out <hi>contradicting</hi> and <hi>Blaſpheming,</hi> and dealing as deſpitefully with the Lords Meſſengers now as once they did: But you finde it not to be ſo with the Gueſts you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite to the Lords Table who refuſeth to Come? or who deales deſpitefully with you, inviting them to Come? we can name hundreds of thoſe, we thinke, thouſands, who deale deſpitefully with the Lords Meſſengers, that will not ſuffer them to Come to the Lords Table; while they Contradict and blaſpheme Chriſt offered them in the Goſpell. And ſo having cleared our way, the ſenſe and ſcope of this Parable, we argue from it againſt this free admiſſion to the Lords Table.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>That they who turne their backes upon Chriſt offered to them in the Miniſtery of the Goſpell muſt not be admitted to Communion at the Lords Table.</q> We take this to be ſo cleare to every one that hath not put out his owne eyes, nor is blinded with light, that to argue it further were to hold a Candle before the Sunne. Yet this more we will ſay; They that tread His moſt precious blood underfoote tendered unto them in the Goſpell, will deale with Him as ſwine like offered unto them at His Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; not poſſible they ſhould reject <hi>Him</hi> at one place and receive <hi>Him</hi> at another, They goe from the place of hearing full of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they goe as full to the place of receiving; Then it muſt needs follow, that they <hi>loath the honey-Comb,</hi> they trample it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-foote,<note place="margin">Prov. 27.</note> as in the one place ſo in th' other.</p>
                  <p>You will ſay, how doe we know that? we are to hope well of all men; they come to the place of <hi>heareing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We anſwer you to that in anothers words, to one that ſaid he kept his Church, ſo may your dogge too: Yea but we heare, ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117965:22"/> may your dogge too, a ſound. Truely Sir, this is not our Engliſh, though yet we allow it, knowing it to be a truth; Alas, Sir, you know they were in the hearing place, and they were hearing, while they refuſed to hearken, and <hi>pulled away</hi> the ſhoulders, and ſtopped their eares, that they ſhould not heare; <hi>Yea they made</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Zach. 7 11. 12</note> They did not ſhutt the eare againſt <hi>audience,</hi> but they did ſhutt the heart againſt <hi>Obedience;</hi> hearing in Scripture account is <hi>obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> is <hi>beleiving,</hi> if we obey not what we heare, we are not ſaid to heare, as you know it is clearely made out to us from <hi>John 5. 37. &amp;</hi> 8. 47. by our Lords owne teſtimony; And truely, Sir, you muſt, (if there be a muſt) to doe your duty, examine your people at this point, whether they have, through their eares, received Chriſt into their hearts, before you admitt them to the Lords Table? But we may Contribute more to this hereafter, onely this we have cleared in the (1) place againſt this your free admiſſion to the Lords Table, That they, (and they are the Greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) muſt not have admittance thither, that have refuſed Chriſt, yea rejected Him in the Miniſtery of the Goſpell; for why ſhould thoſe <hi>tremenda myſteria</hi> be ſo prophaned? why ſhould thoſe be be dealt with ſwine-like by ſwiniſh men? worſe than if trampled under-foote in the face of the Congregation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>WE argue from the Covenant of Grace and mercy by Jeſus Chriſt, that He will be a God and a Father unto us, very gracious for His Son's ſake.</q> And that we may argue it more Clearely, we ſhould give our minds to Conſider, That there is an height and depth, and length and breadth <hi>of grace, love and mercy in this Covenant of God with us.</hi> It is that, which the Saints have laid up (to uſe excellent <hi>Preſton's</hi> words, whereby he yet ſpeaketh) for the foundation of all their Comforts: It hath been the Corner Stone, upon which the Saints have been built from the beginning of the world to this day. There is no ground we have to beleive we ſhall be ſaved; no ground to beleive any promiſe of God ſhall be made good unto us; that we ſhall have the price of the high Calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt, and thoſe Glorious riches of the inheritance prepared for us in Him; we ſay there is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117965:23"/> do ground at all but on this Covenant. All that our Miniſters teach us from day to day are but Concluſions of this Covenant, they are built upon this, God hath made a Covenant, with us in Chriſt, and we are in Covenant with Him. He is our God in Chriſt, and we His people through Him, and have acceſſe to Him by one Spirit. Now hence we argue, THEY THAT ARE who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ignorant of all this, <hi>and will be ſo,</hi> turning their backes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meanes of Gods appointment, whereby to make knowne this Covenant to the Children of Men, and ſay in their heart (the language whereof the Scripture ſpeaketh) <hi>We have made a Covenant with Hell, and with death are we at an agreement;</hi> theſe manner of perſons thus ſottiſh and brutiſh as we have heard, have nothing to doe with the Seales thereof. But thus ſottiſh and brutiſhly ignorant are they, for whome no other plea can be made for their admiſſion to the Lords Table, but that they were borne in <hi>England,</hi> and Baptized there; This therefore is our faith, as to this point of admiſſion, That it is the duty of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt well and throughly to examine their people what knowledge they have of this Covenant, at leaſt what breathings they have after it, and to make out their intereſt to it in the conſcionable uſe of the meanes appointed by God for that Glorious end before they Give, admiſſion to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or Bring their Children to Baptiſme. In our Earthly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as Conveyances of Land, houſes, and the like, we know how bootleſſe it were for us to have nothing to ſhew for our rights and juſt title to them, but a Seale without a writing, or a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant without a Seale; And whereas it is ſaid, we open the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the people, and ſo we diſcharge our duty, and leave them to examine themſelves at that point, for ſo they are Commanded; <hi>But let a man,</hi> i. e. <hi>every man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 11. 28.</note> This preſuppoſeth that, which is moſt falſe, ſaith Learned <hi>Beza;</hi> 
                     <q>That all are able, diligent and willing to examine themſelves, and ſo upon that ſuppoſition to be admitted to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</q> We will deferre this to another place, where we ſhall find this very Scripture aſſured us, <q>That ignorant perſons are no<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Bez.</note> more to be admitted to the Lords Table, than are <hi>Children or madmen.</hi>
                     </q> So we leave this, taking it fully proved, that they who are wholy ignorant what the Covenant is, or what it mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117965:23"/> are not to have admiſſion to receive the ſignes and ſeales thereof; or as our little Catechiſme hath it, They that have no inward Grace, cannot tell what to make of the outward ſigne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>THey are not to be admitted to the Lords Table, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly receive any thing there but <hi>bare Elements bread and wine,</hi> they cannot receive <hi>profit</hi> by it, not having <hi>faith to mingle</hi> with it; faith is a neceſſary ingredient in every Service we doe performe to God, or to our owne Soules; The word ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to us profits not unleſſe <hi>we mingle it with faith.</hi> The word<note place="margin">Heb 4. 2.</note> ſpoken out from us, The word of prayer prevailes not without faith, It is like a Gun diſcharged without a Bullet, which makes a noiſe, and doth no execution. So in receiving at the Lords Table, if we doe not put out the hand of faith, we receive no more there than at our owne Table; faith is to the ſoule, what the eye, eare, mouth, hands, feete are to the body; No Spirituall good comes into our ſoules till Faith by the Word and Spirit comes in and fetcheth it in; And no good can come forth, till faith putts it forth, be it word or deed; If faith be not wrought in us, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Word hath had no work upon us; for that is the firſt grace in the order of time, and to our apprehenſion faith comes in firſt, and drawes all other graces after it, it enliveneth and quickneth the ſoule, it is the Spring of ſpirituall life in us; it is the firſt grace of all; it is ſet downe in ſtead of all, and indeed ſo it is. If we have faith, if we can beleive nothing is impoſſible to us, to doe or to ſuffer, when God calls us thereunto; It was a Sad time with the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> was ſadded at it, and faine would he know how the caſe ſtood with them, ſpecially how it fared with their faith, <hi>when I could no longer forbeare, I ſent to know your faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ: 3.</note> and when good tideings were brought us of your faith, we were exceedingly comforted: for I know full well ſo long as you ſtand faſt in the faith, ye ſhall ſtand like Mount <hi>Zion</hi> in the world, an everlaſting foundation mauger all the powers and policies of Hell-Gates wide open againſt you. To open this a little and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in it, Becauſe indeed it is the very hinge upon which all ſhall turne; When the holy Spirit comes in to the ſoule, conveyed in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117965:24"/> thither by the word (the <hi>Spirit</hi> the Hand of God and Chriſt. His Vicar or Agent here on Earth, does nothing in an ordinary way without the word, The word can doe nothing without the Spirit, it bringeth all at once along with <hi>Him;</hi> All Spirituall things needfull to Salvation; And that the ſoule may take faſt hold on them, and appropriate them to Himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>all theſe are mine.</hi> The Spirit with the Word (for He will not worke alone as the <hi>Word</hi> cannot) workes faith there, and faith workes up the ſoule to Chriſt, for it is the Spirits working.) Its chiefe and maine <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi> And now drawes or ſuckes from that Breaſt of Conſolation all that is deſireable, ſuitable, ſatisfactory, and moſt pleaſant to her. But this is the thing. Faith lookes firſt to Chriſt, the perſon of Chriſt, the <hi>fountaine,</hi> the <hi>Spring-head,</hi> the <hi>Treaſurie,</hi> the <hi>mine</hi> of Gold. Faith lookes to the perſon of Chriſt firſt, it knitts the ſoule to Him, then it lookes to all the good things we have by Him, a world of good things in <hi>Him,</hi> a world of good things from Him, All that tends to Grace and Glory: Yet it is the perſon of Chriſt, that the ſoule of a Chriſtian principally lookes to. The whole word of God, all the divine truths therein revealed, are the object of faith to direct, order and ſway our lives; But yet theſe are not the object of faith, when we looke for peace, for Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and reconciliation with God; Then faith lookes to Chriſt fixedly, wholely, ſolely.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things being premiſed we returne to our Argument.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, They that have not received faith (the Guift of God<note place="margin">Faith is the Mother Grace, where that is in Truth, there is true knowledge, unfaigned live, and Goſpell Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, The graces required in every true Communicant. <hi>John 20.</hi>
                     </note> ſent unto us by the hand of the Spirit with the word) can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme nothing pleaſing to God, nor can they receive any thing from God, but a Cup of wrath; if they continue faithleſſe and unbeleiving, They have not received Faith, no not by all thoſe meanes appointed by God as Conduit-pipes to convey faith and every Grace unto them; they have not received faith, true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith, they cannot receive Chriſt, a true and ſaving Chriſt, a King and Prophet to Rule, governe, and teach them, and a Prieſt to ſave and Redeeme them (a falſe Chriſt and he is many, they may Receive by a falſe faith) they muſt have a true faith, before they can receive a true Chriſt, with all the benefits of His blood-ſhed for <hi>them;</hi> a true faith leades them unto this ſtorehouſe or Treaſury; brings them up to this fountaine <hi>opnod for ſin and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117965:24"/> uncleanneſſe;</hi> layes the ſoule in that <hi>Jordan,</hi> cleanſeth and waſheth it there, bids it waſh and be cleane, bids it <hi>drinke</hi> and be <hi>drunken</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 5. 1. Eph. 5. 18.</note> with <hi>wine,</hi> whereof is no exceſſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> be <hi>aboundantly ſatisfyed.</hi> But without faith none of this can be, It being the very bucket, the mouth of the ſoule. So that a man comeing without faith to the Lords Table, is like a veſſell caſt into an Ocean of waters, that hath no mouth to let any-in: So then <hi>without faith,</hi> without Chriſt, and then <hi>Aliens to the Common-wealth of Iſraell,</hi> and <hi>Strangers from the Covenant of promiſe, having no hope</hi> (well ſet and ſetling) <hi>and without God in the world.</hi> Now are theſe to be admitted to the Lords Table, perſons without faith, and then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſaving grace, for faith is firſt in order of nature? Anſwer this to God, ſee if He will accept of your replie, which we may heare anon. Wee proceed,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, They that have no faith are not to be admitted to the Lords Table, not onely becauſe they receive nothing there, but becauſe they fearefully prophane the Holy things there; They have no knowledge of thoſe things, none at all; and none they looke after, <hi>their ſoule is not good, it is ſtarke naught,</hi> as darke<note place="margin">Prov. 19. 2.</note> as a Dungeon, for what ſhould enlighten it; as noyſome and loathſome as an open Sepulchre, or a veſſell wherein is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,<note place="margin">Prov. 13. 5.</note> for what ſhould diſcover this their filthineſſe to them, that they may appeare ſuch in their owne eyes? <hi>that doe not beleive,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom 15. 31. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> are diſobedient, rebellious, <hi>imperſwadable</hi> ones, <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> men, that is the Apoſtles Character of them; and he makes cleare proofe of it in theſe words <hi>they have no faith.</hi> Are<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> they at the Lords Table? they are <hi>out of place</hi> ſure, as a ſwine is when he is in the Parlour; <hi>abſurd</hi> men, ſo <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Engliſheth it, though <hi>Beza</hi> liketh it not: <hi>Quod mihi quidem abſurdum vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> But our Learned <hi>Reinolds</hi> liketh it well. The Apoſtle ſaith he calleth men without Faith <hi>Abſurd men,</hi> becauſe it is an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and ſottiſh thing for a workman to be without his chei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Inſtrument, and that is univerſally requiſite to every one of his workes; a husband-man without a plow, or a builder without a rule, preacher without a Bible, or a Chriſtian without faith, are things equally abſurd and unreaſonable. What reaſon have we to plead for thoſe unreaſonable men to be admitted to the Lords Table, more than we have for the admitting of ſwine into
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117965:25"/> our Parlour? uncleane ones will make all things like themſelves, as uncleane too, to themſelves we meane.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Perſons that have no faith are not to be admitted to the Lords Table, becauſe they cannot <hi>ſhew</hi> the Lords death there.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>This Scripture Mr. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>: hath corrupted af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner with his gloſſe.</hi>
                     </note> It is a grave and a weighty word that we Engliſh <hi>ſhew,</hi> and we would rather leave it to you to unfold to your people, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch may require one hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es worke But in a word, a worthy receiver, that brings faith with him, he doth with all thankeſgiving and praiſe <hi>ſhew</hi> forth the excellencies of Chriſt, and the Glorious benefits of His bloodſhed upon the Croſſe, the Bounties of His Goodneſſe, and Beauties of His Holineſſe, making an <hi>oſtentation</hi> of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, preaching to every one as he can; This this is it wherein every true Chriſtian is to glory, and he orders his life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; The import of that word as we ſuppoſe. Now they that Come to the Lords Table, and have no <hi>faith,</hi> are no more able to ſhew the Lords death there, than a man of Clouts ſtuffed with Straw is able to gaine the victory in the day of warre.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, And to run over theſe Grave matters, he that comes thither and brings no faith with him, muſt needs receive <hi>unworthily,</hi> that is, other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe than is meete ſuch myſteries ſhould<note place="margin">Neh. 27.</note> be received. And therefore ſhall be held as guilty before God as <hi>Judas</hi> was, who betrayed the body of our Saviour, or as the <hi>Jewes</hi> were, who ſo villanouſly abuſed <hi>Him,</hi> Binding His hands, ſpitting in <hi>His</hi> ſacred face<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and crowning <hi>Him</hi> with thornes, and as the Souldiers were; who peirced <hi>His</hi> ſides, and ſpilt <hi>His</hi> blood, <hi>He ſhall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Free admiſſion is not to be given thoſe, who cannot examine themſelves about their faith, that is, ſearch, digg, goe downe into the fouldings of their ſoules, to enquire what their eſtate is; what it is to be out of Chriſt, or what it is to be in <hi>Him;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Infantes furio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos, &amp; in verbo Dei minime inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uctos. <hi>Bez.</hi>
                     </note> they cannot <hi>examine</hi> themſelves about theſe matters, no more than Children can for they are Children in underſtanding; no more than <hi>mad</hi> men can; for theſe <hi>are mad upon their Idol,</hi> ropro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, diſallowed of God, in a ſtate of reprobation. We will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to <hi>Beza's</hi> Annotations, or rather thoſe to you, which we thought to have been large upon, being ſo full to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Why ſhould faithleſſe men, worſe than Infidells, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117965:25"/> borne and bred in <hi>England,</hi> a land of viſions, be ſuffered to come to the Lords Table? They cannot <hi>diſcerne the Lords Body;</hi> they can put no difference between that bread, which repreſents <hi>the body</hi> of Chriſt Crucified, and Common bread at their owne Tables; nor between the wine there Sealeing to a worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a full diſcharge from all his ſins in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt: No difference can he make betwixt this wine and common wine: And now being ſuffered to come to the Lords Table, he there drinks downe a Cup of damnation in ſtead of ſalvation; a cup of curſing, in ſtead of a cup of bleſſing; and ſeales the Stone upon his graves mouth, where he lies rotting in ſinne, as dead bodyes in their graves, <hi>He eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelfe, not</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 29.</note> 
                     <hi>diſcerning the Lords body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. As you have received mercy and now would ſhew mercy unto everlaſting ſoules, admit not theſe faithleſſe, theſe unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and wicked ones, that cannot ſhew forth the Lords death, cannot examine themſelves, have no diſcernining of the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, admit them not to the Lords Table. They have no faith, then they muſt be full of themſelves, as a veſſell being full, and running over, they cannot Eate and drinke there any other thing but damnation to themſelves. This Scripture alſo Mr <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of fornicators and prophane perſons, as was <hi>Eſau,</hi> fearefully abuſeth, plucking out as he can, the <hi>ſting</hi> of it, ſo as the moſt bruitelike perſon may come to the Lords Table, and not be ſtung by it; oh prophane man and paſt ſhame! he and his booke ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the noſtrills of the Lord and of his people, as the worſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements of the Dragon doth.</p>
                  <p>2. And now Sir, we will ſpare you the labour, if pleaſe you, in making a reply to this; and ours in making Anſwer thereunto. This we heare is ordinarily ſaid; <hi>They were borne and Baptized in a Church, and therefore beleivers:</hi> we like not to make an Anſwer to ſuch a foppery; why! but they ſay they beleive the ſame with the former, they ſay it with their tongues, what ſay they with their hands; ſuch are their words, what are their workes? They may ſay ſo and <hi>Blaſpheme</hi> in ſo ſaying, as was hinted more than once.<note place="margin">Rev. 2. 9.</note> I pray you obſerve it, and let this mocke-faith goe, unleſſe you will whip it like a vagrant, and ſend it backe to the Devill whence it came; We have been ſpeaking of that <hi>faith,</hi> which gives reall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117965:26"/> 
                     <hi>union,</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with Jeſus Chriſt, and of neceſſity brings forth good workes, as a good tree, good fruit, he beares upon a good roote, or rather the roote him, he is planted in <hi>Him,</hi> he beares upon <hi>Him;</hi> Come; when all is ſaid this muſt ſtand, Let a man beleive <hi>truely,</hi> and truth of beliefe will bring forth truth of holineſſe; A true faith, a true hope; true love, true obedience, all in <hi>Truth;</hi> when faith is in Truth, that is, truely ſet, and fixed upon its chiefe and proper object Chriſt Jeſus the Lord. O how doth man boaſt himſelfe to be ſome body, when he is nothing, nay worſe than nothing, but knowes it not: A Beleiver, when he is worſe than an Infidell; And how ſecure doth he lye, (he is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) under the ſhadow of a falſe faith, more ſecure (ſuch is his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, he is very Confident) than a true beleiver, ſuch is his infirmity, lyes under the ſhadow of a true faith. You may heare theſe ſpeake like Saints, and ſee them, if you narrowly marke them, live like Devills; ſo that if their word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> doe not bewray them, their workes quickly will; outſide Chriſtians, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſide Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens; O it is good, and but your duty, Sir, to obſerve men and ſearch them narrowly, before you admit them to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for <hi>all men have not faith,</hi> no not they, many of them, that<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 3. 2.</note> make a profeſſion, and a ſhew of it; You may meete with not a few ſottiſh, and brutiſhly ignorant, and then not ſo meete to ſit at the Lords Table as a ſwine properly ſo called is to ſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t yours: You may meete with ſome alſo, that have a pearle (of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) in their heads, &amp; their hearts as full of poyſon, and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hatred againſt the Goſpell of the Kingdome, and true heires thereof in Chriſt, true Goſpellers, as the moſt venomous Serpents are. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in doctrine, <hi>Recuſants</hi> in lives, having a <hi>tongue</hi> profeſſing for the Truth, and a <hi>life</hi> profeſſing againſt it; faire out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, but within as noyſome as a dunghill, or an open Sepulchre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which yet ſavoureth with them as a Garden of Spices, or bed of Roſes; ſomething reſembling an Heaven in ſhew, when they have an Hell with-in, the heart we meane; ſo you may ſay, have the excellent of the Earth too; but to them it is an <hi>Hell,</hi> as their dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill ſmells like a dunghill; but to thoſe their hell is their heaven here, as their dunghill ſmells with them as aforeſaid, a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Character of a polluted wretch.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:117965:26"/>
                  <p>We would not be miſtaken here, we cenſure no man, we judge him not, we dwell at home, and our ſelves muſt we judge. But upon due ſearch thus you'le finde it to be, even as we have ſaid, and ye may have found it ſo by experience; we may put downe this for a Concluſion; If faith bring Chriſt the fountaine of Grace into the heart of a man, he can no more walke in darkneſſe (of ſin and ignorance, there is a darkneſſe of Spirit of ſorrow, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Childe of light may walke, and you have an excellent booke of it, but) no more walke in darkneſſe than he can doe, that could<note place="margin">Iſaiah 50.</note> carry the <hi>Sun in his hand;</hi> and he may as well carry fire in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and not feele it burne, as carry true Grace in his heart, and not cleanſe his life; But Counterfeits in Grace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to continue ſuch, and to hold ſin, the leaſt ſin-faſt, ſhall become Saints, when an Ape comes to be a man, and Copper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Gold, which is never rejected, but when it would looke like Gold. Beleive it you doe, a beleiver can no more be without Holineſſe, than can a godly man be without godlineſſe, or a true Chriſtian without Chriſt; or than can the Sunne be darke, or the fire Cold. We ſhall crave leave to ſpeake further to you about theſe three grave matters; The <hi>feaſt of the Goſpel,</hi> The <hi>Covenant,</hi> And <hi>Faith;</hi> but we ſhall deferre it till the Laſt, and therewith cloſe-up this Treatiſe. We proceed now in our argueing againſt this free admiſſion to the Lords Supper. In the fourth place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>IT is not according to the practiſe of Chriſt, He gave it <hi>to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> onely, (it is not poſſible, we conceive, to make it out, That He gave it to <hi>Judas,</hi> yet if it could be made out, we have enough to ſay, were this a place for it) He gave it to <hi>Diſciples</hi> onely (<hi>Judas</hi> himſelfe, if there, looked like a Diſciple, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>like</hi> one) and by ſo doing, he preſcribes his Miniſters what they are to doe (ſo we conceive) as to thoſe adminiſtrations to<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ea quae perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ua ſunt, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia ſunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis</hi> Mark. 14. 23.</note> the worlds end. And here we are not bold to ſay, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>:</hi> your Champion, doth fearefully pervert Scripture, wreſt and Crooke His bleſſed Lords practiſe, to the Countenancing of his owne curſed and crooked doings, <hi>and they all dranke of it;</hi> Well, what then? his inference now (hold your Noſe if you cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117965:27"/> the deadly ſtinke of the Dragons excrements) <hi>Therefore let all Come that will Come to the Lords Table.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Good, Sir, Give us leave to pauſe a little, while we take theſe things into our thoughts; is there not a Cauſe we ſhould ſo doe? When we heare this Reaſonable Creature, we call a man, a ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and a Miniſter too, as he calls himſelfe and would be called, ſpeake thus unreaſonably, as if he was as much wanting of Reaſon as he is of Grace; unreaſonably ſaid wee? Is it not too ſlight a word, doth not he ſpeake blaſphemy? doth he not blaſpheme the Bleſſed practiſe of our Lord and Saviour, which He hath ſet as a patterne for all His people to practiſe after? <hi>And they all dranke of it.</hi> So may ye, all ye <hi>drunkards;</hi> and yee, all ye <hi>uncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> and you, all you <hi>worſe than Infidells;</hi> and you all, <hi>deſpiſers of the Goſpell;</hi> and yee all, that never thought of any other <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> but that which ye have made <hi>with ſin, death, and hell;</hi> And ye all, that have <hi>faith,</hi> though it have no more life, than a poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Stone, hewen timber, or a doore-naile, no-matter how dead it be, 'tis a <hi>faith,</hi> that will ſerve the turne to entitle them to theſe holy things, <hi>drinke ye all of this,</hi> as we read thoſe Diſciples did, <hi>and they all dranke of it.</hi> But Sir, is not this Blaſphemy? Wee are willing to make you Judge here, becauſe you judge ſo well of the man; Come in here all <hi>ye of the world,</hi> for whome that ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">John 17. 9.</note> never opned His mouth and prayed; Come in hither ye knowne enemies of the <hi>Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> ye <hi>belly-ſervers,</hi> ye that <hi>minde Earthly things, drinke ye all of this;</hi> ye that Crucifie to your <hi>ſelves</hi> the <hi>Son of God afreſh,</hi> and put Him (as they doe by their<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> vile uſage, and abhominable Converſation) <hi>to an open ſhame, drinke ye all of this;</hi> and ye all, who have <hi>trodden under-foote,</hi> as they can, The <hi>Son of God,</hi> and have counted <hi>the blood of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> (wherewith they profeſſed themſelves ſanctified) an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>thing;</hi> and have done little leſſe than deſpight to the Spirit of Grace: All ye drinke of this: And to make a round number, and full, and ſo to fill the Table, that as there is no want of roome, (for a nationall Church is wide enough, and rich for ſupply,) ſo there may be no want of Gueſts, Come ye all ye <hi>ſtiffenecked and uncircumciſed in heart, and eares,</hi> yee <hi>doe allway reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as your fathers did ſo doe yee.</hi> What though? ye ſee what proviſions are made for you notwithſtanding; All ye drinke <hi>all of this,</hi> for the bread ye have taken already.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:117965:27"/>
                  <p>Sir, we have proceeded hitherto with ſome regret, yea with ſome indignation to our ſoules; yet for the Cloſe hereof, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you Conſider, That by the gracious allowance of their Lord and Maſter, they <hi>His Diſciples all dranke of it.</hi> The Lord <hi>Himſelfe</hi> putting the Cup into their hand, but theſe all afore-mentioned have drunke and dayly doe drinke of it by Man's Allowance. <hi>Drinke ye all of this,</hi> ſaid Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and what He bad them doe they did it, and <hi>they all dranke of it.</hi> Drinke ye all of this, ſaith This-man, without any the leaſt warrant from God, and how readily is he obeyed? what he bad them doe they did, and they <hi>all dranke of it;</hi> Though he that bad them, and they that did as they were bad, have done and ſtill doe as Croſſe and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the mind of Chriſt, as He Himſelfe is to <hi>Beliall,</hi> or to Anti-chriſt, which is to be argued in the fift place, ſo ſoone as we have put downe this for a concluſion, That God hath not onely given us His Word for a ſecondary rule of Righteouſneſſe to walke-by, but Himſelfe, and His Son, the Higheſt patterne, the primative or Originall <hi>prototype,</hi> the cleareſt Copy without blot, the faireſt example of Holineſſe. Whence we conclude, That Chriſt Jeſus our Lord is both the <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>patterne of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> The <hi>principle</hi> within His people; the <hi>patterne</hi> of Holineſſe, without or before them. Therefore will all His ſervants, who in deſire and endeavour approve themſelves Faithfull, doe as He did, following-on in his ſteps. He that ſaith, <hi>He abideth in Him,</hi> ought himſelfe alſo to <hi>walke even as He walked,</hi> 1 John 2. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>AS this free and Common admiſſion is contrary to the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Chriſt, ſo it is as it muſt needs be, contrary to the mind of Chriſt; we are forced, as we conceive, to argue diſtinctly from theſe, the <hi>practiſe</hi> and <hi>mind</hi> of Chriſt; though <hi>His</hi> practiſe Cleareth <hi>His</hi> mind, as <hi>His</hi> mind <hi>His</hi> practiſe; But yet we ſhall argue differently from it, and we ſhall be breife in it It is cleane Croſſe and Contrary to the mind of Chriſt; why? Becauſe it is ſo pleaſing, and well agreeing, and full-up to the minde of the world, free admiſſion to the Lords Table is. The mind of Chriſt and the mind of the world, commonly called the <hi>Church</hi> there,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117965:28"/> doe ſtand as Croſſe and Contrary each to other, as doe <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> the greateſt oppoſites; or remoteſt extreames; What is the mind of Chriſt, cannot be the mind of the world, and what is the mind of the world, cannot be the mind of Chriſt, but moſt Contrary thereunto; And to make full proofe of it, let a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that hath the mind of Chriſt, as every Godly perſon hath, and then liveth-up to it, as it is revealed to Him in His Word, and acteth thereafter, in giving out, or with-holding thoſe ſacred ſignes and ſeales of His body Crucified, and His blood powred forth, he ſhall finde, that he <hi>tormenteth the dwellers on the Earth,</hi> the Common people commonly called the <hi>Church</hi> there, who have no other plea for their Church-ſhip, but that they were once waſhed. The <hi>mind</hi> of Chriſt, no other than the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt</hi> in His word, is unto ſenſuall <hi>men,</hi> not <hi>having the Spirit,</hi> as the morning is to the evill doer, even as the ſhadow of death. But let a man doe Contrary to the minde of Chriſt, and give out to theſe ignorant Brutiſh ones, and will be ſuch, the fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, water to their Babes, bread and wine to themſelves, and he gratifies them in the higheſt way of Gratification; he gives them their hearts deſire, and now from that day forward, they will put on high account upon themſelves, they will not thinke of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves below the thoughts their Miniſter rates them at, they will account themſelves, ſith he hath accounted them ſuch firſt, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints.</hi> You remember who he was, that, when he would doe a man a miſcheife, he would Give him a ſute of apparrell, as rich as ſilver and gold could make it, and now the man (a proud creature, and the worſe he is the better he thinkes of Himſelfe) values himſelfe, his inſide we meane, according to the Rate of his outſide, and ſo as the Beaſts you read of, <hi>ingentes rollunt animis;</hi> he was proud by nature, more proud by accident, now that he is put into ſuch a dreſſe. The application is plaine, Take heed Sir, of dreſſing up the people at the Lords Table, (though they delight as much to be dreſſed, as ever a childe in yeares did, in new and fine Clothes) in a <hi>Saints dreſſe,</hi> becauſe he was borne and Baptized in <hi>England,</hi> whereas they cannot make it out they ever heard a word from Chriſt, yet that onely is <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing to make Saints,</hi> being obeyed and beleived. You under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the purpoſe of this, and therefrom how contrary your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117965:28"/> are to the mind of Chriſt; for can that have any agreement with the minde of Chriſt, which hath ſo full an agreement, with the minde of His enemies and adverſaries all over the Nation? We proceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT VI.</head>
                  <p>ALL are not to be admitted to the Lords Table, becauſe all are not viſible Saints: But none but viſible Saints were to be admitted to Communion at the Lords Table, as you ſo well know, that know ſo well the Church Stories, And thoſe primitive practiſes: And truely we are loth to minde you in thoſe things<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ne accedant ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi examinati.</hi> Calv. Ep. 278. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>it in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ratio arcea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, donec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum oſtende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint.</hi>
                     </note> you are or ſhould be able to inſtruct us, however your practiſe be Contrary; But this is the thing we cannot reach-to, that you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe things ſo well, and your practiſe be not ſo well, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe commonly <hi>intellectus currit cum praxi &amp; praxis cum intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectu;</hi> Therefore we doubt there is ſome failing in your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, becauſe you have not given it-up to God, If ſo you ſhould know they were trained up and Catechiſed firſt, and yet they ſtaid a while before admittance, till they could make proofe, that they were taught, and ſo they had gained ſome Competent knowledge of thoſe things they were there to receive, together with their <hi>repentance toward God,</hi> and <hi>their faith toward the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And you can tell us moreover, for we are in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with you but Children, and as yeſterday in theſe things, That huge perſonages, Emperours and the like, have thruſt as preſumptuouſly unto that Table as did <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the King, to burne<note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.</note> Incenſe before the Lord; or as men and women of the world or Church there, Children of Diſobed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence, doe now adayes; but have been withſtood, as he was, and as theſe ſhould be, we thinke, by the Miniſters of the Lord, and thruſt away with the breath of tthoſe words ſpoken to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah;</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>It belongeth not to you, Sir, how great ſoever you are at your owne Table, to thruſt into this, before you have given ſatisfaction to the Church of Chriſt, for your abhominable doeings againſt Him.</hi>
                     </q> So they thruſt him and them away, and ſo they were reproved, as you ſhould thruſt away your nominall <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> members of the world the Church there, whoſe Chriſtian Name doth adorne them, as a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117965:29"/> Jewell doth a ſwine in his ſnout. But thus it was once, viſible<note place="margin">Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> promiſcuè qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſlibet admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt porcis &amp; canibus &amp;c. <hi>Calv. Ep: 278.</hi>
                     </note> Saints were to be admitted, (and ſurely if there be a Communion of Saints on Earth) there they ſhould be ſeene at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and why now viſible Devills?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p>IN the 7th place, we would mind you of what the Lord God of hoſts ſaith to them, that will contend with Him; <hi>Remember the Battle, doe no more.</hi> If you will contend for this <hi>free admiſſion,</hi> you contend with God, to whome you muſt anſwer this with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters. He ſaith and ſo ſay His faithfull Servants with Him; <hi>Ye ſhall not proſtitute theſe ſacred things to ſwine and dogges.</hi> But what ſhall we more ſay, time would faile us, to tell what <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> had rather ſuffer, even the ſpilling of his own heart blood, rather than give out the Seale of the ſame to <hi>non-Diſciples,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners of it, how high and great ſoever. We purpoſely paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what <hi>Cyprian, Martyr, Muſculus, Marlorate, Ambroſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See <hi>Marlor:</hi> on Revel. 11. 1, 2.</note> and thoſe fore-mentioned, about free admiſſion to Baptiſme, what theſe ſaid and did, as to theſe matters, very much to our purpoſe; We will onely heare what <hi>Zanchi</hi> ſpeakes to this, and <hi>Calvin</hi> after him, becauſe it is urged very much, <hi>That you doe your</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Potitur a me cura, in Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> 
                     <hi>duty when you bid your people beware;</hi> No ſaith <hi>Zanchi,</hi> 
                     <q>yee doe not your duty, you neglect the beſt part of it, and ſo you pertake of their ſinnes, ſuffering unworthy ones to pertake at the Lords Table; yee draw upon your ſelves <hi>Eli's</hi> vengeance, by giving ſuch an allowance, When you doe not <hi>frowne</hi> upon theſe, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them with your eye; you violate Charity and are guiltie of iniquitie, your owne and their's, when you ſuffer men to damne themſelves with a Sacrament, when you might reſtraine; yea yee are guilty of their damnation, as we are of that man's death, whome we ſuffer with his ſword to ſtabb himſelfe, out of whoſe hands we could have kept that Inſtrument of death;</q> ſo farre <hi>Zanchi.</hi> And give us leave to adde a word more thereunto, becauſe we know it is the Miniſters common plea, we warne all our people, mention unto them the fiery indignation of the Lord againſt unworthy receivers; This will not doe; you admit them under the notion of Saints, why ſhould they thinke themſelves
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117965:29"/> Devills? You may threaten hell to them, but they will take hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Read Mr. <hi>Coll. p. 14.</hi>
                     </note> and thinke they have good right ſo to doe, while you bid them take and eate, take and drinke—you know what followes; They never ſwallowed wine ſo ſweetly at the Taverne, as they doe now <hi>damnation</hi> at the Lords Table; But they thinke not ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have brought them into ſuch a fooles Paradiſe, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them beleive they are what they are not, no more than an Ape is a man; <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples</hi> in name onely are Saints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. O Sir, what ever others doe, be you aware here, what you ſuffer the people to doe: give them ſcope here, we mean full liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or free admiſſion, like a rope long enough to a wicked man, and you may tell your ſelfe what he would doe, by what you have ſeene him doe ſo often; You know no creatures almoſt, but man, loves that, which will be its owne bane; indeed we have heard ſay that ſheepe catch at that graſſe moſt greedily, which ſooneſt rotts them; we are ſure it may be ſaid of us men, what the Greeke Father ſaid of ſome in his time; <hi>Give us that which is ſweete, though it choake us;</hi> wine at the Lords Table; Why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſweet words which follow; but how miſtaken! one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wretched man ſeekes a bleſſing in a direct way to a Curſe; happineſſe, in the way to miſery; life in the way to death; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the way to hell. If you conſider all this, you will doe more than give your people warning againſt the next Communion day. You will tell them and aſſure them, you have Scripture warrant for ſo doing; That they muſt ſhew more for their Admiſſion to the Lords Table, than this, That they were <hi>borne and Baptized in a Church,</hi> or elſe they ſhall be dealt with as doggs and ſwine, And droven from the Lords Table, as we drive ſwine from ours, And you cannot doe them a greater reall favour, than ſo to deale with them; And to preſſe you and your brethren of the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion with you unto this, we will remember you of <hi>Calvin's</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: lib. 4. cap. 12. ſect 5.</note> words; That a Miniſter, who admitteth unworthy perſons to Communicate at the Lords Table, is altogether as guiltie of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as if he ſhould proſtitute to dogges the Bleſſed Body of the Lord Sacramentally in the Bread.</p>
                  <p>And to prevent this horrid uſage, and Contempt done to that bleſſed thing, he thus preſcribes and expects it to be done: <note place="margin">Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l. 302. Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i oleviano.</note> 
                     <q>Let no perſon be admitted to the Lords Table, till he hath profeſſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117965:30"/> his faith; and put it not off to the day before the Supper be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred; But goe to the man's houſe, if he hath one, and looke over his family, let him give you an account what order he obſerveth in his owne houſe, and at his owne Table, before he be admitted to the Table of the Lord; and how peaceable and helpfull he is among his neighbours, and note well how well he ruleth his Children and Servants, whether he hath <hi>theſe in ſubjection with all gravity;</hi> obſerve alſo this with it, or elſe you obſerve nothing to purpoſe, whether there are not ſome ſloathfull and wicked perſons in his houſe, who would runne to the Lords Table, but are very ſlacke and more than ſlugges when they ſhould goe to the place of hearing:</q> We ſee now how truely it was ſpoken of him, he would chooſe an hundred deathes, rather than ſuffer the prophanation of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. This is ſo full to our purpoſe, that we thinke fitt to make a full point here; and Come in the next place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O tell you M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Baxter's</hi> judgement as to this point of free admiſſion, Surely he is point blanke againſt it, as farre from M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hs:</hi> judgement, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H:</hi> is from the<note place="margin">Bap: 96.</note> Truth. Thus ſaith M <hi>Baxter,</hi> 
                  <q>Though I admit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred to the Sacrament, yet I adminiſter it to none that I know to be unbeleivers; nay, nor that I judge not probably, or hopefully <hi>beleivers.</hi> In another booke thus he ſaith; for my<note place="margin">Aph. App. 108.</note> ſelfe I doe adminiſter the Sacrament to none that doe not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly profeſſe their aſſent to every fundamentall Article of faith expreſſely mentioned to them, and their Conſent; that Chriſt ſhall their Lord and Saviour, and that they will faithfully and ſyncerely obey His Scripture Lawes.</q> Can a man ſpeak more fully to the point againſt free admiſſion? Truely he might be numbred among the men of the Congregationall way, but that it would not be for his honour. And yet he may thanke himſelfe for that; for he indeed hath numbred thoſe holy ones amongſt the uncircumciſed ones, thoſe ſons and daughters of <hi>Belial;</hi> And dealt little leſſe unmercifully with them, than did the perſecutors
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117965:30"/> in old time deale with the faithfull witneſſes of Chriſt, <hi>they put them into beaſts skins, that ſo the dogges might hurry them to death.</hi> But let that paſſe, which, we hope, he will not paſſe without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, not <hi>making a difference;</hi> he ſpeakes well for the way, we wiſh he walkes with a right foote in it: though it is as much above us to reconcile him to himſelfe, as a Mountain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is above a Mole-hill, and poſſible ſo others may finde it alſo. Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im what he ſaith in a third booke; <q>
                     <hi>You</hi> remember when you called<note place="margin">R: 4. 52.</note> me to be your Teacher, You promiſed me under your hands, that you would faithfully and conſcientiouſly endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving every truth, &amp; obeying every command, which I ſhould, from the word of God, manifeſt unto you; I now Charge your promiſe upon you;</q> he goes on bending to his higheſt end <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt.</hi> We borrow his words, doing him or them no wrong, we hope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bending to our ſcope; <q>There is not a more apparent Truth, than that the Table of the Lord ſhould not be polluted, nor a more apparent duty, that the Stewards in Gods houſe ſhould look to it, that doggs &amp; ſwine be not admitted to Come thither. The ſacred Scripture ſpeaks clearely out to this; And we thinke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if a Child ſhould ſhew us Scriptures, and ſpeake to us the word of God, we ſhould not dare to diſobey it.</q> We might goe on in his words; But we paſſe them, taking this onely from them to juſtifie the Miniſters in the Congregationall way for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing a Covenant to their people. So it ſeemes M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B.</hi> did doe. We mention it not, as if the Miniſters of Chriſt have no better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrant, than his example; they take their warrant, as we hope he doth, from the Scriptures of God, and example of all the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who can make out their intereſt in the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Gods grace with them by Jeſus Chriſt, and now enter into <hi>Covenant</hi> one with another, to walke together as <hi>fellow-helpers of the truth</hi> in the fellowſhip of the Goſpell according to the rule thereof, with full conſent of minde and heart to promote the proſperity of the ſame, and the Intereſt of Chriſt in their ſoules, and through the Nation; And they that ſticke at this, and are ſtrangers to it, and will be ſo, doe, as is to be feared ſticke as much at the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God to give up themſelves in full obedience to it and to Him who is the <hi>Mediator of it.</hi> We have ſeene M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</hi> manner with his people, and ſurely it is Commendable, and he hath a ſure
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117965:31"/> word for it; That Miniſter and people, They, that owne him for their Miniſter, ſhould walke together in a Goſpell-way by a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell rule, full-up, in deſire, and endeavour, to That Covenant <hi>Jehojada</hi> made between him and all the people, <hi>that they ſhould be</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lords people.</hi> O it is good to be the ſame we profeſſe to be, <hi>the Lords,</hi> and to make cleare proofe that we are His by our cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect walking, watching over each other in our way; rendring an account of our way, when required ſo to doe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eareing each others burthen, ſupplying each others wants, pertaking of each others graces, doing all things as becometh a <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> alwayes doing or receiving good. O it is good to ſtand bound with theſe Cords, bonds and engagements of God upon our Spirits, <hi>we are the Lords people,</hi> He hath taken us into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Himſelfe; In deſire and endeavour we will walke as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh a people in Covenant with their God, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Certainly nothing is done decently and in order, where this Covenant is not, or, where it is, and is not <hi>ſtood unto,</hi> there is a <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and <hi>every evill worke:</hi> The way of the world right, of a Nationall Church there; whoſe way is as broad as the Nation is, and puts them, that walke in it, to <hi>no Coſt,</hi> none at all: therein they may walke with all their uncleanneſſes upon them, onely they muſt put themſelves into a Comely dreſſe againſt the next Communion day, as is becoming <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> who ſay they are ſuch, and their word muſt be taken having no other teſtimony of their goodneſſe but from themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers like themſelves or from the miſtaken Charity of the Godly, if it be poſſible for Charity it ſelfe to be miſtaken in thoſe, who have no other plea for their <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> but that they were baptized.</p>
               <p>But now the way of Chriſt with His people in Covenant with Him, and in fellowſhip one with another, is a ſtraight and narrow way, it pincheth the fleſh ſtill, yea it is ſtill <hi>ſtorming</hi> of it: And the orders therein preſcribed, His followers are ſo <hi>ſelfe-denying,</hi> ſo <hi>holy</hi> and ſo <hi>heavenly,</hi> as few, that hold for a Nationall Church will ariſe to the obedience of them; which made ſome prophane Men profeſſe (they were of a Nationall Church ſure enough) when the reformation began in <hi>Luther's</hi> time; <hi>That they would rather live under the government of the Turk, than where all things
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117965:31"/> ſhould be ordered according to the word of God.</hi> We thought fitt to adde this, thereby to juſtifie the Brethren of the Congregationall way in Goſpell fellowſhip one with another, and in deſire and endeavour keeping cloſe to the Covenant of their God, taking the hint of it from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>B<hi rend="sup">s</hi>
                  </hi> manner with his people.</p>
               <p>To the cloſe of this Chapter we crave leave to adde, a very good man's jealouſie, Godly we beleive it to be, as he himſelfe is; <q>We thinke our brethren goe beyond their warrant, while they take Saints of the firſt magnitude onely into fellowſhip; God hath a people of all ſizes, there is the ſame holineſſe, but not the ſame degree of true holineſſe in all Beleivers.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We make bold to tell our perſwaſion, as to this godly jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in this matter (which may paſſe as farre as his heare-ſay, whereupon he grounds, we thinke, what he ſaith, which we, in favour of his pietie and goodneſſe, doe call His jealouſie, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it to be godly) That the Brethren of the Congregationall way, who walke with a right foote therein, are, as deare Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought to be, <hi>followers of their deare Lord</hi> in this perticular; ſo farre from refuſing the weake in faith, as that they doe invite and encourage ſuch. The leaſt Breathing after Chriſt, the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Him, how deſireable a ſight is it? how acceptable with them? how encouraged, promoted, countenanced by them? how pleaſing and welcome to them? even as the bruiſed reed was, and the ſmoaking flax to their Lord and Maſter. Not the weake but the dead, To uſe that good man's words; not Children, but <hi>Baſtards;</hi> not comers towards Chriſt, but reſiſters of Him in the meanes of drawing to Him; doe theſe Brethren purpoſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, where they ſee any meaſure of true godly feare, any degree of graciouſneſſe, they gladly admit: God forbid they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the meaneſt, as to the world, or in Grace; no they Covet the pureſt, and take the weakeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:117965:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſhould now in the next place, ſet downe the Charge of the Lord to all thoſe that have the Charge of the Sanctuary, of thoſe holy things there, that they make a ſeparation betwixt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and the vile. But this is ſo legible every where all along the Scripture, that we might ſave our ſelves and you the trouble; And indeed this ſecond part of our worke exceeding its proportion, we will deferre what we ſhould have ſaid here to the Laſt Treatiſe. And ſo we come to that we promiſed, therewith to cloſe the reſult of this ſecond debate, as we did the former, and ſo to cloſe up this part. We have made bold to give you a word of exhortation once already, we are bold againe to give you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word, and to proceed in it, we know the manner of an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſon, he takes that <hi>pearle</hi> thankfully as given him from God, though brought unto him, as the good Prophets meate was, by a <hi>Raven:</hi> A reproofe to him is welcome for what he hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, much more an exhortation that he may not ſo doe, being taken from the mouth of God, as you ſhall finde, we hope, this to be; withall we are every one <hi>taxed</hi> to pay a <hi>Contribution</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the good of ſoules, and well-fare of That Body, whereof the Lord Chriſt is the head and the Saviour, and this we can doe no other way but this.</p>
               <p>Sir, we can clearely ſpeake this unto you, we wiſh you <hi>Gaius</hi> his proſperity; that you may <hi>proſper as your ſoule proſpereth;</hi> They you, with your people, they with you may walke in the Truth by Goſpell rule; we doe Conſider with you, That you, being a Miniſter of note, and we hope a <hi>Godly Man,</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of you, as you reade was ſaid of a Godly Noble-Man, You are <hi>norma publica, a publique Standard unto your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> who indeed, for the moſt part, are very <hi>Apes,</hi> taken by imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by what they heare you ſay or ſee you doe, <hi>Non ad ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſed ad ſimilitudinem vivimus,</hi> was the old Complaint; we take words upon truſt, our Miniſter ſaith it, and there is an end: Thoſe brave diſcreete and generous <hi>Bereans</hi> did not ſo, They
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117965:32"/> heard <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas with all readineſſe of minde,</hi> yet they did not receive the <hi>word</hi> upon their word as ſpoken from them (though they might have been beleived before any) but they <hi>ſearcht the Scriptures dayly, whether thoſe things were ſo, therefore many of them beleived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is out of uſe in theſe dayes, whence it is there are ſo many beleivers in name, and Infidells indeed. You are, we hope, the more carefull what you ſay before them, for we queſtion not your doings out of Gods houſe, and ſo to make way to what we far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intend.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Wee humbly entreate you, you would forbeare to doe what we know others doe, gather-up all the filths once viſible now legible in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Creete,</hi> to beare-out the filthineſſe of their owne: To alledge their want of order and good diſcipline, thereby to juſtifie their owne diſorders, and no diſcipline at all: To make their defects and faileings, to plaiſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over their owne more than <hi>faileings,</hi> their abominable doeings in God's Houſe; Remember we ſhould they had but the <hi>dawnings</hi> of the day of the Goſpell, we have the <hi>noonetide</hi> thereof; And that wee are to walke not by the darke ſide of the Cloud. And let us tremble to juſtifie ſin by ſinne, as we ſhould at that judgement, which the Lord God makes-<hi>up of ſin,</hi> puniſhing ſin with ſin. Bid your people follow holineſſe; ſtudie to be quiet, and to be pure, a courſe cleane contrary to the world, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, the Church there, they follow unholineſſe, and ſtudy impiety.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Tremble (oh that you could) to be found in the number of the Corrupt Miniſters all over the Nation; theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes did, now doe, and alwayes will oppoſe <hi>Reformation,</hi> the Diſcipline of Chriſt in His Church, the breathings of all His Saints in the world, <hi>That all things may be done according to patterne;</hi> as viſibly held out now before them, as was that in the Mount, as to all Church-adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And Sir, If you looke after this way, looke for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in it, and from your Brethren. As ſure as it is an <hi>holy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 5. Jer. 40. 7. John 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Acts 26. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>way,</hi> ſo ſure it is a <hi>perſecuted way, contradicted</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemed,</hi> and this ſpecially by Brethren. But can this diſcourage you? It was ever ſo; The Lord Chriſt was oppoſed Cheifely by the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117965:33"/> Preiſts, Scribes, and Phariſees; And <hi>Luther</hi> profeſſed that he<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k 6. 26.</note> found more enemies in the <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yſters,</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> than he did out of prophane and wicked places; <hi>perſecution</hi> is as the hand that points you, <hi>there is the way of holineſſe, walke in it:</hi> If o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> finde no perſecution then ye are out of the way, <hi>for ſo perſecuted they the true Prophets,</hi> pointing them to this way; but for the falſe Teachers that had bid the people runne-on in their <hi>owne way</hi> of ſin and death pleaſing in their owne eyes, <hi>all ſpake well of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 7. 52. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. 3. 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>them.</hi> You will find it to be ſo; and <hi>fore-warned, fore-armed.</hi> And the Nominall Beleivers, titular Diſciples and Saints, ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to their owne way, a looſe and evill way, the way of the world, of a Nationall Church there, theſe will deale moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully with you. A juſt judgement, ſhall wee ſay, or rather a fatherly Correction, (if the Father of mercies make it ſo to you) That ſo they ſhould returne your kindneſſe to them, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them, when time was, to the Lords Table, upon this ſcore onely, <hi>They were borne in England and Baptized there.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E come now to that we mainely intended, and you know <hi>we cheifly inſiſted upon to prove:</hi> That your free admiſſion to the Lords Table is Croſſe to the holy rule, we ſhould walke by; to the practiſe and minde of the Lord and deare Saviour, and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the minde and manner of all thoſe, that are followers of Chriſt, and cannot <hi>ſtint themſelves with any degree of holineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 John 3. 3.</note> their Lords owne <hi>purity</hi> being their <hi>Coppy.</hi> And here we more than touched upon three things, ſpecially the <hi>Word preached,</hi> how they preſſed to that place, and liſtned to it when they came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Secondly, the <hi>Covenant of Gods free grace by Jeſus Chriſt bleſſed for ever.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Faith;</hi> upon that we were the more large, all beareing upon that, being the hinge of all.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, this is our earneſt deſire, That you with your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would looke over this againe, and lay your doctrines, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and practiſe before your people, to that Standard; for we chooſe to ſpeake in that number. And</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:117965:33"/>
               <p>1. Doe ye preſſe upon your people the neceſſitie of heareing? and before you admit them to the Lords Table, doe ye take time and place to ſearch them to the bottome, what they have profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by heareing? You know hereby they are <hi>hewen,</hi> and made poliſhed Stones, and ſo fitted to be laid in the Lords building; we truſt you doe not doe as the Maſter of your <hi>Lord</hi> doth, <hi>Poliſh your people at the Lords Table.</hi> Surely they are to be made readie, as thoſe <hi>Stones</hi> were, before they ſhould have your admittance to<note place="margin">1 Kings 6. 7.</note> Come thither. And, to proceed, doe you aske what is that grace they muſt have before they can profit? In our zeale for the Lords Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yours and your peoples precious ſoules, we ſhall queſtion you in theſe grave points, and ſo returne in all thankfullneſſe your godly jealouſies touching us and our way, by putting it upon your thoughts what your way is with your people, and how with them, They with you walke therein. You know, but have you as you can, made your people know it, That preaching is the Chariot, that carrieth Chriſt all about the Nationall Church, we had almoſt ſaid the world; And the onely Appointment of God in the Spirits Hand to plucke them out thence, as <hi>Lot out of Sodome.</hi> It is the <hi>Ordinance</hi> ſanctified of God for the begetting of faith in the beginning or <hi>Alpha</hi> of it; ſo in the encreaſings of it to the <hi>Omega</hi> or perfecting of the ſame: It is that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hereby that, which is begun is perfected, and that maintained which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; It is that, whereby the abundant riches of Grace through Jeſus Chriſt are Conveyed unto us by <hi>Covenant</hi> (we have ſaid all)<note place="margin">2 Tim: 1.</note> by Covenant; <hi>life and immortality is brought to light by the Goſpell preached, the Miniſtery thereof;</hi> there is not onely an unfolding of the gloriouſly excellent things of Chriſt, but there is grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Spirit to beleive them. Thereby th' underſtanding (that everlaſting dore) is opned to Jeſus Chriſt, Him that is true, the true God and eternall life; Now th' underſtanding cloſes with<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 20.</note> Him, or rather He by His Spirit with the underſtanding. He <hi>is Truth:</hi> The will and affections are drawn-out to Him alſo, Oh how good is He to the Soule! what a lovely object, altogether <hi>deſires.</hi> By preaching all this is done; it is the Chariot of the<note place="margin">Cant. 5.</note> Spirit, it is the meanes that worketh <hi>faith;</hi> which is the marriage of the Soule to Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> uniteth the ſoule to Him, planteth it in Him, maketh it one with Him: And now ſhe begins to know the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117965:34"/> abundant riches, and glorious excellencies of Her Husband; and the way of Conveyance of all theſe unto her by <hi>Covenant;</hi> but ſtill the firſt doore that is opned to all this is the <hi>eare,</hi> and it is opned by heareing; by heareing the eare is made able to heare, we meane by the word; the Spirit boreth it, and now <hi>faith</hi> comes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and fetcheth all-in, the ſoule ſtands in need of, Chriſt and all, and all as ſure as a Covenant of God, with His people in Chriſt can make it. Hold you to this ſtill, we meane hold your people to it; <hi>faith comes by heareing,</hi> it hath the ſtamp and inſtitution<note place="margin">John 10. 17.</note> of God upon it; and <hi>heareing by the word of God;</hi> This was the ground of the Apoſtles faith (not all the miracles they had ſeene,) <note place="margin">John 2. 22.</note>
                  <hi>They Beleived the Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>the word which Jeſus had ſaid.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 13.</note>The ground of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> faith alſo, <hi>In whom ye alſo truſted after that ye HEARD the word of truth,</hi> the Goſpell of our Salvation. The very end of all that is written touching Chriſt, <note place="margin">John 20. 31.</note>and is preached of Him, <hi>that ye might beleive</hi> &amp;c. Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge this point home, ſo your Lord Chargeth you, and examine your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about their faith in God. They will ſay, they bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve, <note place="margin">Numb. 22. 18.</note>They will ſay as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, <hi>My God,</hi> and ſo will they ſay, <hi>our God,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hoſea 8. 2</note> we <hi>know Thee.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 16.</note>Heare them now how they can make out what they ſay; Doe they know Him, whom they call theirs? here you are like to find your people as groſſely ignorant, as were their fore-fathers, of <hi>whome ye ſay,</hi> ſaith our Bleſſed Lord, That <hi>He is your God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 54, 55.</note> yet, <hi>ye have not knowne Him;</hi> We, that have accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our tongues to lying ever ſince we were borne, muſt not be credited in what we ſay, till you have heard us making out what we ſay; by giving <hi>a reaſon of the hope that is in us,</hi> for truely thus it is with us for the moſt part: We underſtand neither what we ſay, nor what we affirme in God's matters. Yea we commonly ſay, we know the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> when we oppoſe the meanes appointed by God to convey this knowledge to us; Now you ſhall doe well to tell us, <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus;</hi> That we are as well qualified to have Communion with Chriſt at His Table, as a Wadd of dried ſtubble, is to have Communion with a Conſuming fire, and doe no more enjoy Him there, than midnight enjoyes the Sunne. And that we doe indeed and in truth no more deſire Communion with Chriſt, <hi>the King at His Table,</hi> or in any other place, than darkneſſe can deſire Communion with light, or <hi>Beliall</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117965:34"/> with Chriſt. We are groſſely ignorant of what we doe, when we approach, by your allowance, the Lords Table. It is not poſſible<note place="margin">Fruimur Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis. Igno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i multa Cupido.</note> we can enjoy that we have no knowledge off or acquaintance with; nor can our deſires move towards an unknowne object. Good Sir, ſpeake theſe things out to us (your people we meane:) We are ſomewhat the larger here, a point of ſo high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being Confident alſo of this very thing, That you find your people cleane croſſe to their Rule, as your Brethren doe every where, <hi>ſlow to heare,</hi> and <hi>ſwift to ſpeake</hi> for the Lords Supper: We conceive the reaſon thereof to be this, In a heareing place they cannot heare one word, if it be the true word of God, which is pleaſing to fleſh and blood, it ſpeakes death to their luſts, if ever it ſpeakes life to their ſoules. Therefore they hate the word (a killing word) deadly, becauſe they love their luſts dearely. They will have none of that <hi>meate which endureth to everlaſting life,</hi> none of the wine of the Goſpell, but as much bread and wine as you will, and as often as you will at the Lords Table; and the reaſon of this is, becauſe thereby their luſts are fattened and cheriſhed.</p>
               <p>2. Therefore Sir, preſſe upon your people the neceſſitie of heareing; and obſerve them well, at their coming to That place, and as narrowly their ſitting and attending there. And having done this, doe not thinke you have done all your duty, or more than the leaſt part of it: They may give you the eare, while they give the fleſh, the world, and the Devill their heart; You know, and you muſt teach them to know it: It is eaſier to heare an hundred Sermons, than to practiſe one. Therefore let them know, you will deale with them apart and alone, you will ſingle them out of the throng of the world, or National Church, and out of the crowd of the Common hearers, before you admitt them to eate and drinke at the Lords Table; They ſhall give you a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of what they have gained by all their heareing.</p>
               <p>This was the practiſe of the Lord Chriſt, when He was upon the Earth, He ſpake alone and apart with His Diſciples. And indeed the Lords people love to be ſo dealt withall alone and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the throng and tumult of the world, or a Nationall Church there. <hi>The Spouſe of Chriſt is modeſt, and will not come
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117965:35"/> to Thee in the throng of worldly Company and employment,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard. Come my Beloved,</hi> ſaith the Spouſe, <hi>let us goe forth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 7. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>into the fields, and lodge in the Villages.</hi> Let us get from the Tumult of the world. The Bridegroome of His Church, loves to finde His Spouſe alone, retired into a Chamber; And ſo muſt His <hi>Paranymphs</hi> too, give the Church a meeting in ſome reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red place.</p>
               <p>3. Now becauſe this lyeth under ſo much—obloquy, we crave leave to ſpeake a little to it, in paſſage onely in this place, we are not ignorant how this Aſſembling together of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is reproached, if not blaſphemed thus; <q>
                     <hi>At your private meetings, errours and haereſies, what not, have been fomented, brooded upon and hatched.</hi>
                  </q> Truely this cannot be denied, it is ſo cleare and evident; The Father of lyes with his Children muſt have their meeting places too, wherein to lay their heads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, plotting and contriving (we are not ignorant of his devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) how they may miſchiefe if not ruine (for they levell to ſhoot ſo high) the Church of Chriſt, and build up their owne <hi>Babel;</hi> But here is your Comfort, they are Maſters neither of the meanes nor of the end: their endeavours are above their performances, as their <hi>malice</hi> is above their <hi>witt,</hi> which (for that is it's doome) <hi>drinkes-up the greateſt part of its owne poiſon,</hi> or like Gun-powder conſumes it ſelfe in the flame it hath cauſed. But ſhould not this teach us to aſſemble our ſelves together as often as we can, there to lay our heads together, and contrive the moſt Compendious way of building-up the Church of Chriſt, and our ſelves therein, the moſt contemptible parcells thereof? O it is good to be plotting for the <hi>Church</hi> and for the <hi>Truth,</hi> for this is to be plotting for <hi>eternity.</hi> O that all would meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, here and there and every where, there to plott how to avoyd Satans plotts; Let it be our awakening that Satan is plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; And that our time is ſhort; opportunity, the flower of time, ſhorter; our talents are many, our accounts ſtrict; our Judge Impartiall. O let us not forſake the Aſſembling our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is.</p>
               <p>Having taken off, as we could, (we intend more hereafter) that reproach wherewith the enemies of the Lord have reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117965:35"/> the foote-ſteps of His annointed-ones, we proceed to put it upon your thoughts, whether it be not your duty to give a meeting to your people in a private place, there and then to learne from them what they have gained by all their heareings? what a worke is wrought in them or upon them by the word of His grace with power? It is not what ſhew they make in words, what doe they, that you may beleive them? or how humbly doe they ſpeake, ſo as you may conceive hope there is ſincerity at the <hi>bottome?</hi> a ſparke of fire, for there is <hi>ſmoake:</hi> a little ſtrength, though but as much as a <hi>reed</hi> hath; it is in the gaineing hand. O how would he, and deſireous is he, in the uſe of meanes, to gaine more? Indeed it will be worth your labour to take time and place for the ſearching out of this: You muſt find-out their deſire after the ſyncere <hi>milke of the Word,</hi> by their <hi>growth</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> It is a Common ſaying amongſt us, <hi>ſhew me not the meate but the man;</hi> So ſaith the great Shepheard to His ſheepe, and ſheweth what His under-Shepheards ſhould ſay to them too, Not ſhew me the hay that I have given you, but the wooll and the milke, that is, ſhew me the fruits and effects of all your heareing; What ſupernaturall worke can you tell us off? Is the life of Grace put into the heart, by the Spirits working together with the meanes thereof, the word of His grace? Is there a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row change, not of the <hi>actions</hi> onely, but of the <hi>Nature</hi> wrought in them? The Spirit with the Word changeth the inward man with the outward, it changeth the whole frame of the ſoule, it is no halfe-change, for that is to be halfe a Chriſtian, or <hi>allmoſt,</hi> which is to be an Infidell indeed. <q>It is no light alteration, but as the old ſtamp (theſe are excellent <hi>Preſton's</hi> words, one of the uſefulleſt Preachers in His time that was in the world) muſt be obliterate, before the new can be imprinted; and as the old building muſt be pulled downe, before you can ſet up a new; So this old nature of ours muſt be broken to peices, and new caſt and moulded, (<hi>for we are bell-mettle</hi>) before a man can be made a living man, which is done by the infuſion of Supernaturall qualities of Grace and holineſſe, ſupernaturall he ſaith; for even as the earth may bring forth graſſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon flowers of it ſelfe, but it muſt be plowed and ſowne before
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117965:36"/> any choice herbs and plants can grow there; even ſo thoſe common natures, which we all have, may bring out things that are morally good; but before they can bring forth fruits of true righteouſneſſe we muſt be plowed and ſowen; plowed, that is, man muſt be broken in heart for all his animoſities and indignities put forth, when time was, againſt Chriſt, and the Goſpell of His Glory;</q> for all thoſe ſlightings of Spirit he found in himſelfe of thoſe glories tendred to him in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Gods grace, when he was full of himſele, and <hi>wanting nothing,</hi> and knew not his owne beggery and nothingneſſe, and <hi>want of all things;</hi> broken in heart for all this.</p>
               <p>Upon thoſe heads, Sir, your examination muſt paſſe, if you doe according to the manner of Gods people; and a ſet time and place muſt be appointed for it: If you cannot goe from houſe to houſe, as <hi>Pauls</hi> manner was, and <hi>Calvins</hi> alſo, as you heard, then muſt they come to yours. Could our Voyce be heard all over the Nationall Church, all the world over, this is it we would ſay and preſſe upon the Miniſters there; <hi>You muſt give your people a meeting time and place for it,</hi> there to take an account of them what they have profitted; And you muſt not take their bare, <hi>ſay ſo,</hi> their profeſſion onely, they are <hi>Belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> beleive them not, not their owne word, bring their words and lives both to the <hi>teſt,</hi> or <hi>touchſtone of the Word,</hi> for they expect admittance to the Lords Table. This muſt be done firſt, diligent ſearch muſt be made, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given-in, how fitt they are and prepared gueſts for That Table; what kinde of faith they have? whether it be active or dead? They are Cunning enough, yet perhaps not enough to deceive you, unleſſe you are willing to be deceived; you can aske them how it was wrought in them? and by what meanes in the Spirits hand? But ſtill remember them how they and their faith muſt be tryed; And let this come often into your minde, what ſelf-ſeekers and ſelf-pleaſers we are; and that <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing and ſelf-ſeeking</hi> is the firſt ſtone that is laid in the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite's building; Therefore if he be let alone he will flatter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his death-bed, yea to Hell, perſwading himſelfe ſtill that he is an heire of Heaven, being borne in <hi>England</hi> and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:117965:36"/> there. And indeed this will ſerve the turne to make him a member of a Nationall Church, or as you know who ſaid it, a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tizen of the world; But if he make cleare proofe that he is a member of the True Church, you muſt take ſome paines with him in point of examination of him in theſe matters. And your hardeſt worke will be to remove that ſtone you have helped to lay, beareing him up with this conceite, that he is a <hi>Belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Diſciple, a Saint,</hi> becauſe borne and baptized in a Church, remove but this ſtone, and downe falls the building. The har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt worke, we beleive, you have to doe, is to plucke downe, what ye have built-up; That Caſtle in the Aire raiſed-up, as high as Heaven by a falſe hope or preſumption rather; but now there is a poſſibility they may be built-up as true <hi>Beleivers, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> are, in whoſe building the firſt ſtone that is laid, is <hi>ſelf-deniall,</hi> and <hi>fleſh-crucifying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the points you, we hope, will treate about with them, and ſearch them in; and doe not be put off, which was hinted before, with their bare profeſſion; you know we may make a bare profeſſion, and deny Him in our workes, whom we doe profeſſe in words; and declare our ſelves abominable and diſobedient, and unto every good worke reprobate. We can<note place="margin">Tit. 1. 16.</note> lye as faſt as we can goe, it is ſo naturall to us, for ever ſince we could goe, <hi>we have gone aſtray; and ever ſince we could ſpeake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>we have ſpoken lyes.</hi> What mighty reaſon is there, and what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement unto you from hence to doe this, If you will doe your duty? give the people a meeting, we meane, thoſe that you intend to meete at the Lords Table; and hope anon to meete them in heaven; Give them a meeting that you may try upon Scripture Grounds, what alteration is made in them, what change? They were eſtranged from the womb, they were gone aſtray out of the way, are they yet reclaimed? can they ſhew for it, that they are returned? have repented unto life, and doe beleive in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt? Above all, put them from their vaine boaſts, and out of their fooles paradiſe, that they were borne in <hi>England</hi> and Baptized. Indeed it is a glorious outward priviledge to be borne where the Goſpell Sunne ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but if we gaine no inward glory by it, we are made twofold
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117965:37"/> thereby more the Children of Hell than the Pagans are (which was ſaid before, but we <hi>are dull of heareing</hi>) O bid them beware therefore, it is for their life, which ſhall laſt as long as the long day or night of Eternity.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>You remember <hi>Cecil,</hi> Lord <hi>Burt: Counſelled his Son not to build his houſe upon any impropriation;</hi>
                  </q> well knowing it would be built upon a ſandy foundation: Yet it did but endanger a houſe, which, built-up never ſo ſtrong, and ſettle it never ſo ſure, though upon a rocke, yet as ſure as it was builded-up, it muſt fall downe. But to build the houſe of our Confidence, and for a Miniſter to make us bold in it, upon this; That we are to be accounted <hi>Beleivers, Diſciples,</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> and to be admitted to the Table of the Lord, becauſe we were borne in <hi>England,</hi> this is to build upon a quickſand. <hi>If a fox goe up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 4.</note> which was ſcornefully ſpoken of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> wall, <hi>it ſhall even breake downe the wall of this their Confidence.</hi> It ſhall not need, though yet they ſhall meet with it, a ſtormy wind to rent it,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zr: 14.</note> To put a cloſe to our good Counſell, and this ſecond part of our undertaking.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ermine,</hi> they ſay, is ſo neate a Creature, that if a puddle be on the one ſide, and dogges on the other, it will rather run into the dogges mouth there to be devoured, than into the pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſo much it hates filthineſſe. And you know, who ſaid it, and as they ſaid they did, If fire were on the one hand, and ſin on the other, they would rather be conſumed than defiled. Certainly it is ſo with the people of God; doe you in theſe matters what you will, they will doe as God Commands them, they will ſeperate the precious and the vile. And they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, Counſell, and pray, you and your brethren, while they have an hand to move, or a tongue to ſpeake, that you would Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what you doe, and what you ought to doe in Gods houſe, as to thoſe ſacred adminiſtrations there, leaſt upon your neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect therein, you become the greateſt ſinners in the World: The ſinnes of the whole Nation, the Church, theirs become yours.</p>
               <p>O Conſider, <hi>Qui peccata non corrigit aliena, facit ſua,</hi> He that doth not correct, or hinder the doeing of a Crime, the polluteing of the Lords Table, when he can, and it is in his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117965:37"/> hands to doe it, he is no leſſe guiltie of the Crime, than is the offender himſelfe. There is a perſon preſumes to come in his filthineſſe, The Miniſter, ſuch as he is, conſenteth to it, ſaith in effect come, and welcome; This <hi>Conſenter</hi> is as deeply guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as is the <hi>preſumer,</hi> you know who ſaid it. Why but this Miniſter is as full of Charity and hope too, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> is, <hi>hee hopes well of all:</hi> Yea but whereon doth he ground his hope? no other ground but this, That perſon was borne in a Church and baptized there. So was the verieſt Rebell your ſelfe have knowne, or heard off, made longer by the neck, or ſhorter by the head, therefore this hope is like the houſe of a Spider, the beeſome of deſtruction will ſweepe it away, the man dyes and his hope with him both together, and at one inſtant, which may make us more obſervant of the words that follow, which we borrow of our Learned <hi>Reinolds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was a beaſt ſlaine for touching the Mount, and ſhall not a man of vile and beaſtly affections be puniſhed for touching the Table where our Lord is preſent? No; we would ſay, The vile and beaſtly Miniſter deſerveth rather of the two to be puniſhed, who admitts, alloweth, yea invites men of Beaſtly and vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to come to That Table where the Lord is preſent; The allowance of a thing done (which was ſaid before and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too often ſaid) is as good as the Commiſſion for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, ſaid our excellent <hi>Jewell.</hi> We would adde to this the prayer of a good man. <hi>Lord deliver me from mine other mens ſinnes, which I may have made mine, if not by Command, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell or Conſent, yet by Connivance, give me Repentance for them good Lord, and forgive them.</hi> It is a knowne ſaying, and bids you beware, for <hi>qui in conſpectu populi male vivit, quantum in ſe eſt, omnes ſe videntes interficit:</hi> He that ſinneth in the open view of the people, doth as much as in him lyes, to murther all that looke upon him, and behold him ſinning.</p>
               <p>The application is eaſie, and ſummed up in this, the <hi>Preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> and the <hi>Conſenters</hi> ſhall be puniſhed together, and which ſhall receive the ſoreſt puniſhment is not hard to determine: <hi>The actions of the Rulers being the Rules for the Ruled;</hi> We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you all by the mercies of Chriſt, we would peſwade you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117965:38"/> by the terrour of the Lord, whoſe Stewards you are, and by the bleſſing yee expect, from, in, and upon the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, that yee would Conſider theſe things, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things than theſe, as the Spirit called upon, in the reading His word may ſuggeſt unto you, and fully reſolve you at this point, That your great Lord and Maſter, to Whome yee are ſhortly to give an account of your Stewardſhip, will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to have holy things prophaned, as if Common and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane.</p>
               <p>Therefore this is our perſwaſion grounded upon the word of God, and practiſe of His people, Ye muſt appoint time and place, where and when your people may give you the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there to know <hi>the ſtate of your flocke,</hi> which yee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 19. Col. 4. 8.</note> know at ſuch a diſtance in the publique place. You cannot there in that publique place, doe as <hi>Paul</hi> did, and as you ought to doe: <hi>You know how we exhorted and comforted, and charged every one of you,</hi> as a father doth his Children, (every <hi>one of you</hi>) he had them alone and apart, ſure, there is a neceſſitie of it, a <hi>Muſt</hi> for this; yea though it were according to that offer or deſire rather of your Learned Brother and Neighbour, which is, <hi>That all perſons in a Chriſtian Common-wealth, ſhould give an account of their Faith, before they marry and become parents</hi> (and why not before they are admitted to the Lords Table?) Wee profeſſe heartily, this were a notable <hi>expedient,</hi> and would helpe much for the removeing of that Barr, which hath letted and will lett, till it be removed, the admiſſion of their Infants to Baptiſme by Godly Miniſters; But wee may deſire, rather than hope, that this Courſe will be taken, That all before they marry and become Parents, ſhall give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Faith: Though we conceive this Courſe ought to be taken with thoſe, who for nine Moneths have lived in uncleanneſſe, That theſe ſhould not be married the tenth moneth, before they had made their Repentance as publique as their offence was; For Certainly this ought not to be, That a Couple be <hi>married to day,</hi> and be <hi>made Parents to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow,</hi> Surely They did not give an account of their faith. This was done in the world, the Nationall Church there in a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:117965:38"/> Parochiall Church, very few miles off from you, for the part hath the ſame name, with the whole, and a part in this huge, we had almoſt ſaid, monſtrous Church, is too great for ſuch ſmall things as theſe to be looked after</p>
               <p>Indeed Sirs, ye muſt Contract and Epitomize your Church, for if this Courſe were taken, your Godly Brother preſcribes here; Notwithſtanding you muſt have your private meetings with your people.</p>
               <p>Surely after a ſerious debate betwixt your ſelves, about theſe matters, you will finde it (we humbly conceive) your onely way to Abridge and Contract your huge large volume of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leivers, (who can ſhew no more for their faith but their Infant Baptiſme) into a little little volume (they muſt and they will goe cloſe together, they will never be looked over elſe, though every one of you had an hundred eyes) taking one of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and ten of a thouſand, and this may Comfort you in this troubleſome and vexatious worke, (ſo fleſh and blood will finde it yours and theirs) That one believer indeed, who can give a reaſon of the hope that is in him, is more excellent, than are an hundred of thoſe, who can alledge no more for the Cleanſing of their hands, and purifying their hearts, but that, when time was, their faces were ſprinkled with water. Now when ye ſhall ſet upon this worke, ye muſt, we conceive, appoint a ſet time and place to meete at.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe there is a ſpewing Caſt upon theſe meetings, in uſe onely as we conceive amongſt the Brethren of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall way, we meane all thoſe that ſeperate from the world at the Lords Table (for the word, <hi>Independant,</hi> is very unbecomeing Churches or Creatures, it was Caſt-in by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and adverſary of all righteouſneſſe) we were ſaying becauſe this way, and theſe meetings lie open to much Obloquie, from that wicked one, the Father of lyes, and all His Children; as that theſe meetings are the Nurſe, or <hi>vis plaſtica,</hi> the very fomenting Cauſe of errors and hereſies; beſides it Chargeth the Holy Brethren with <hi>ſeparation,</hi> or making a <hi>ſchiſme</hi> or Rent from their Brethren, and ſo in a manner excommunicates them from their Company.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:117965:39"/>
               <p>Wee intend, with Gods helpe, to ſpeake ſomething to this, but becauſe this part of our worke hath exceeded its propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the gravity and weight of the matters here under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and maintenance ſo requiring, wee thinke it fitt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it to the Laſt, and to cloſe with it, and our Spirits, if the Lord be pleaſed, alltogether, and all in one; for wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to turne-in unto you after our manner at the end of our worke.</p>
               <p>Now in the Cloſe of this Chapter we would ſpeake to the Chriſtian Reader (whoſe eternall good is full in our eye, which makes us to bend after it night and day) in our <hi>Reinolds</hi> words; <q>Though we may have our Miniſter's leave and free admiſſion to the Lords Table, yet let us not venter to receive ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred things with unwaſhed hands, as matters of meere Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, faſhion, or formalitie; But let us looke unto that High <hi>Authority,</hi> That ordeined them; on that <hi>holy Mouth</hi> That Bleſſed them; on That <hi>Arme of Mercy,</hi> That exhibits them, being ever aſſured, That as Chriſt hath one hand of Bounty and Redemption, which reacheth forth life to the worthy Receivers, So hath He another of Juſtice and power ready to avenge the injuries and Contempt that ſhall be done to His owne holy Inſtitution.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A little after he ſpeakes to <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>people;</hi> to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; Let not your hands againe play the <hi>Judas</hi> by delivering Him againe unto Jewiſh and ſinnefull ſoules, which will Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie againe unto themſelves the Lord of glory. To us the people, Let not us take His pretious blood into our hands, rather to ſhed it than to drinke it; and by Receiving the body of Chriſt unworthily, make it as the ſop was to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> even an Harbenger to provide roome for Satan.</p>
               <p>Who is wiſe and he ſhall underſtand theſe things? pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and he ſhall know them? for the wayes of the Lord are right, and the Juſt ſhall walke in them, but the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors ſhall fall therein. That ye may be ſuch, we Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you all to God; and the word of His Grace, which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:117965:39"/> is able to build-you: up, and to give you an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all that are ſanctified. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with your Spirits. Grace be with you, AMEN.</p>
               <p>⸪</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
